<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a book entituled An account of the Church Catholike where it was before the Reformation; and whether Rome were or be the Church Catholike. Wherein is proved, that the Catholike Church never was, nor can be distinct from that which is now called, the Church of Rome. By R.T. Esquire.</title>
            <author>R. T.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 230 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T42</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221978</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833220</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833220</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37695</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64146)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2065:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a book entituled An account of the Church Catholike where it was before the Reformation; and whether Rome were or be the Church Catholike. Wherein is proved, that the Catholike Church never was, nor can be distinct from that which is now called, the Church of Rome. By R.T. Esquire.</title>
                  <author>R. T.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 165, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Boughen, Edward.  An account of the Church Catholick.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Boughen, Edward, 1587?-1660? --  Account of the Church Catholick --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church --  Catholicity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37695:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To a Book entituled, AN ACCOVNT OF THE <hi>Church Catholike;</hi> Where it was before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; And whether <hi>Rome</hi> were or <hi>be the Church Catholike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is proved, That the Catholike Church never was, nor can be diſtinct from that which is now called, <hi>The Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. T.</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Concordes omnes ſumus, unum &amp; idem ſentientes: quare qui ſocietatem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram devitat, is nè lateat ſinceritatem veſtram, quòd ſeipſum à tota Eccleſia abrumpit.</hi> 
               <bibl>Baſil. Euſt.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Paris.</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37695:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37695:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO A late Book, Entituled <hi>An Account of the</hi> CHURCH CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THough every idle Pamphlet deſerves not the pains of an anſwer, yet ſince new and dangerous Doctrines have ſo far over-ſpread this Nation, and taken ſuch firm root in the hearts of the people, that any defence thereof (though never ſo weak) ſhall be readily imbrac't and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly magnified; I eſteemed it not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37695:3"/>
un-neceſſary, to endeavour by this Reply to undeceive the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luded multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o are commonly carried away ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the authority of ſome perſon (in their opinion) eminent, then by force of Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhould much wonder, that ſo wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thy a perſon, as report ba's repreſented</hi> D. Boughen <hi>to the world, ſhould be the Author of ſo unworthy a Pamphlet, did I not conſider the horried effects of pride and malice, how they not only tempt wretched ſouls out of the right path that leads to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall felicity, but ſpur them on alſo to a violent oppoſition of Gods ſacred truth, till at length they break out into open blaſphemy againſt God and his holy Church, for which God forſakes them, leaving them to their impious and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errors, to maintain which, the moſt learned and ſubtill of all Heretiques are forc't to fly to fallacious and ridiculous Arguments, which though to ſome unwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reader they may at the firſt appearance ſeem to carry ſome ſhow of truth, yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more mature examination they will be plainly diſcover'd to be but falſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfull colours; and ſuch are all the Arguments in theſe Anſwers to the two Letters of Mr.</hi> T. B. <hi>which I doubt not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37695:3"/>
but I ſhall evidently demonſtrate to any impartiall reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. Firſt then Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> deſires the Doctor to ſhew him the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> diſtinct from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in her Communion: The Doctor anſwers, <hi>That the particular Church of Rome is to the whole Catholike, as a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular member is to the whole body; and therefore as the whole body is diſtinct from a particular member, or a particular member from the whole body, ſo is the particular Church of Rome diſtinct from the whole Catholike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rub up your Logick <hi>Doctor,</hi> or let me adviſe you to go once more to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and converſe while with the young Sophiſters, who will tell you of a fallacy call'd, <hi>Ignoratio Elenchi;</hi> which indeed runs through almoſt your whole book: For let us ſet theſe two Propoſitions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt each other, and then ſee whether we can diſcover any contradiction between them.</p>
            <p>1. Prop. <hi>The Catholike Church is not diſtinct from the Church of Rome, and thoſe in Communion with her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Prop. <hi>The particular Church of Rome is as diſtinct from the whole Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, as a particular member is from the whole body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37695:4"/>Where is the contradiction? if both theſe Propoſitions may be true (as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they are) where is the concluſion contradictory to the Propoſition? But let us help the <hi>Doctor,</hi> and form his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into a Syllogiſm, and then perchance we may diſcover a contradiction.</p>
            <p>Ma. <hi>Every particular member is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the whole body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Min. <hi>But the particular Church of Rome is a member of the whole body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concl. <hi>Therefore the particular Church of Rome is diſtinct from the whole body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt here ask again, where is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory Concluſion to Propoſition? but perchance we wrong the Doctor, in making that his <hi>concluſion,</hi> which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for his argument to the concluſion contradictory. Let us try that way then, and ſee what will follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The particular Church of Rome is to the whole Catholike, as a particular member is to the whole body:</hi> Ergo,</p>
            <p>The Catholike Church is diſtinct from the Church of Rome, and thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion with her.</p>
            <p>An excellent conſequence, which every young Sophiſter will laugh at. But let us try one way more, for I would fain make ſomething of it; let us help the Doctor with another Syllogiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37695:4"/>Ma. <hi>The particular Church of Rome is diſtinct from the whole Catholike.</hi> But Min. <hi>The Church of Rome, and thoſe in Communion with her, is the particular Church of Rome.</hi> Ergo:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Church of Rome, and thoſe in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with her, is diſtinct from the whole Catholiks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, I confeſſe, is ſome apparency of contradiction in this concluſions but then what a ridiculous <hi>Minor</hi> is here! By the ſame way of argumentation I will prove <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and the <hi>Suburbs of London</hi> to be within the <hi>walls of London.</hi> Thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ma.</hi> The particular City of <hi>London</hi> is within the walls of <hi>London.</hi> But:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Min.</hi> The Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> and the City of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> adjoyning there unto, are the particular City of <hi>London. Ergo:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> and City of <hi>Weſtminster</hi> adjoyning thereunto, are within the walls of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Minor</hi> were as true as the <hi>Major,</hi> the concluſion would neceſſarily be true, but the <hi>Minor</hi> is as falſe as yours, and yours as this; for you muſt know, good Doctor, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in Communion with her, are as much diſtinct from the particular Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37695:5"/>
City of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> are from the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect..</hi> 2. Beſides, there is great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and the particular <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and the <hi>Catholike,</hi> being <hi>Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nama's,</hi> ſignifying one and the ſame thing: And though in that demand of Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may, in <hi>ſenſu diviſo,</hi> be limited to the particular Church or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſe of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet <hi>in ſenſu compoſito,</hi> that is, being joyned to the following words, [and thoſe in Communion with her] the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is of as full and ample la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itude and extenſion, as the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church. And thus may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd that triviall and childiſh objection againſt theſe words, [<hi>Roman Catholike</hi>] as if they implied a contradiction, they being but (as I ſaid before) <hi>Synonima's,</hi> both expreſſing the whole Church in her ampleſt latitude; for the Church of God is <hi>Catholique,</hi> in reſpect of her Faith, <hi>Roman,</hi> in reſpect of her denomination; <hi>Catholike,</hi> in reſpect of her doctrine; <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> in reſpect of her diſcipline; <hi>Catholike,</hi> in regard ſhe is not conſin'd to one Nation, People, or Kingdome, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites the whole world to her Faith and Communion, willingly imbracing all that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37695:5"/>
will come unto her; <hi>Roman,</hi> in reſpect all particular Churches and perſons whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that are within the Communion of the Catholike Church, are united in, and ſubject to one Head, the Biſhop of the particular Church, or Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing S. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, and appointed by Chriſt to be his Vicar on earth. Thus have we vindicated that expreſſion of [<hi>Roman Catholike</hi>] from contradiction; that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination <hi>Roman,</hi> added to the <hi>Church,</hi> being as univerſall, and having as large a ſignification as the word <hi>Catholike,</hi> which not withſtanding might have ſe med an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary addition, had it not been long ſince occaſion'd by ſome Heretiques, thereby to diſtinguiſh true from pretended Catholikes, for thoſe Heretiques well knew, that they could neither juſtifie their new doctine, nor draw people to their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, but by uſurping the name and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le of <hi>Catholikes,</hi> therefore the word [<hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>] was added to [<hi>Catholike,</hi>] that thoſe Heretiques that had forſaken the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> might not deceive the vulgar under the notion of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. And here by the way Doctor, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to obſerve, that there was never any Schiſmatique, or Heretique, nor any
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37695:6"/>
Sect, or Congregation of men profeſſing the name of Chriſt divided from the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church,</hi> but did either actually or originally ſeperate themſelves from that Church, which is now call'd and ever was, ſince the Apoſtles times, the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and therefore muſt neceſſarily have formerly been in Communion with the ſame Church, which is an argument unanſwerable, that there was never any Catholike Church diſtinct from that, which is now call'd the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> or <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. But in the examination of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I have diſcover'd another fallacy in the Doctor, which the <hi>Logicians</hi> call, <hi>à dicto ſecundum quid, ad dictum ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer.</hi> For though the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in ſome reſpect, <hi>viz.</hi> as ſhe is the particular Dioceſſe or Sea of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> may be call'd a particular Church; yet as ſhe is the Center and Fountain of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> in whom all the particular members of the <hi>Church Catholike</hi> are united, ſhe is, and may be truly and properly call'd, the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church.</hi> And now, good Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, the diſcovery of theſe two fallacies might ſerve for a full and ſufficient an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to (almoſt) your whole book. But let us proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:37695:6"/>5. Now the Doctor begins to muſter up his arguments againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to prove ſhe is not the <hi>Catholike Church.</hi> And firſt, <hi>If the Church of Rome</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>he the Catholike Church, where was the Catholike Church before She became a Church?</hi> Here I expected the Doctor would have begun to ſpeak ſenſe, but it will not be. Let us then examine the Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was a time before Rome was a Church, therefore at this time the Church of Rome,</hi> and thoſe in Communion with her, (for thoſe words Doctor, muſt not be left out, though you are pleaſed to take little notice of them) <hi>is not the Catholike</hi> Church: Or thus. <hi>There was a</hi> Catholike Church <hi>before</hi> Rome <hi>became a</hi> Church; <hi>therefore now at this time the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe in Communion with her, cannot be the</hi> Catholike Church: What ſtrange conſequences are theſe? as if the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> cannot take Her particular denomination from <hi>Rome,</hi> though there were a <hi>Catholique Church</hi> before <hi>Rome</hi> was converted to the Chriſtian Faith. But to anſwer you in a word, before S. <hi>Peter</hi> tranſlated his chair from <hi>Antioch</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> could not take its denomination
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37695:7"/>
from <hi>Rome,</hi> but afterwards it might, and did, and that denominanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Roman</hi> it re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ains to this d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, and ever will, till S. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor ſhall tranſlate his Sea from <hi>Rome</hi> to ſome other City, which (in all probability) neither you, Doctor, nor I, ſhall ever live to ſee.</p>
            <p>6. But let us examine this argument a little further. Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> deſires the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to ſhew him the Catholike Church diſtinct from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in Communion with Her: The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor anſwers, <hi>That there was a</hi> Catholike Church <hi>before</hi> Rome <hi>became a</hi> Church; <hi>and therefore that was not the</hi> Roman. Here the Doctor ha's ſpoke ſomething, though nothing to the purpoſe, for who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver queſtion'd that concluſion? The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ha's forgot himſelf again, for his concluſion ſhould have been this, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the</hi> Catholike Church <hi>was distinct from the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe in communion with her;</hi> and then let us ſee what a fine argument here will be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was a</hi> Catholike Church <hi>before</hi> Rome <hi>became a</hi> Church; <hi>therefore the</hi> Catholike Church <hi>was distinct from the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with her.</hi> Very pretty. Rome <hi>was no</hi> Church <hi>at all; therefore the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:37695:7"/>
Rome <hi>was diſtinct from the</hi> Catholique Church. You muſt not ſay Doctor, that I impoſe this concluſion upon you, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is your own, and you think it ſo ſtrong, that you urge it again, Sect. 22. and though you have not thus ſet it down in expreſſe terms, yet is it neceſſarily involv'd in your diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>7. But I have not yet done with this monſtrous argument. Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> deſires the Doctor to ſhew him the Church <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> diſtinct from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in Communion with her, for the laſt 1100. yeares: The Doctor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, that <hi>there was a Catholike Church before</hi> Rome <hi>became a Church.</hi> Here we ſhall have another fine conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was a Catholike Church before</hi> Rome <hi>became a Church,</hi> viz <hi>ſomewhat above 1600. years ſince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the Catholike Church ha's been diſtinct from the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe in communion with her, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe laſt 1100 years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt excellently concluded, Mr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor; in brief, the effect of the argument is this.</p>
            <p>There was a time when <hi>Rome</hi> was no Church at all, therefore for theſe 1100. years laſt paſt, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37695:8"/>
and thoſe in Communion with her, have not been the Catholike Church.</p>
            <p>Juſt ſo will I prove that D. <hi>Boughen</hi> has not been a Doctor of Divinity for theſe five years laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>There was a time when D. <hi>Boughen</hi> was no Doctor at all, therefore D <hi>Boughen</hi> has not been a Doctor of Divinity for theſe five years laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>Into what a Labyrinth of abſurdities has the poor Doctor caſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>8. Let us now proceed to the next ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,, and ſum it up, as far as it is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, into a ſyllogiſticall form.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Rome be the Catholike Church, then if ſhe be Orthodox, the Catholike Church is Orthodox; if ſhe be heretical, or ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical, the whole Church muſt be hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and ſchiſmatical; but the Catholique Church was never heretical or ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, and yet the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>has been miſerably ſchiſmatical &amp; heretical; ſchiſmatical, as is to be ſeen in</hi> Platina <hi>&amp;</hi> Onuphrius, <hi>when ſhe had ſomtimes two, ſomtimes three Biſhops together, a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, a treble-headed, a monſtrous Church. Therefore Rome cannot be the Catholike Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure the Church of Rome was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo monſtrous as this argument. The
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37695:8"/>
Doctor is fallen ſo deep into a fallacy, that he cannot tell how to get out. M. <hi>T. B.</hi> demands one thing, and the Doctor layes about him to prove another. But let us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the argument.</p>
            <p>If by <hi>Rome</hi> you meane the particular Church, or Sea of <hi>Rome;</hi> firſt, it is imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, ſecondly, I deny your conſequence, at leaſt, as to its latter part, for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church ha's not that neceſſary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence on the particular Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> as that ſhe muſt be hereticall or ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, when <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo. <hi>Rome,</hi> as it is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Sea, is but a member of the Church Catholike, and therefore if ſhe ſhould by ſchiſm or hereſie cut her ſelfe off from the Catholike Church, yet would the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church remain in her integrity and purity, as a man would not ceaſe to be a man, according to his eſſentiall parts, though ſome corrupt and incurable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were cut off from the body; but if you mean by <hi>Rome,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in communion with her, I then deny your ſuppoſition, or your minor propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to that part; for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in that latitude is not at all diſtinct from, but is the very ſame with the Church Catholike, which can never be hereticall or ſchiſmaticall; wherefore if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37695:9"/>
the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ha's had ſometimes two, ſometimes three pretended Biſhops together (as you ſeem to have learnt out of <hi>Platina</hi> and <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> though you cite no particular place in thoſe Authors) yet there could be but one true Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> one true Head of the church, the reſt being meerly pretenders, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they themſelves, and all thoſe that adhered unto them were ſchiſmatiques, and as long as they obſtinately continued in their ſchiſm, they were no members ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Catholike Church, or the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Catholique Church ſtil remaining pure and en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire, and the Sea of Rome a true member thereof.</p>
            <p>9. But the Doctor goes further, and charges the Church of Rome with hereſie, even from the confeſſion of her own men.</p>
            <p>I muſt be bold to tell you, Doctor, that your charge is as falſe as your doctrine: There was never any Catholike that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in communion with her, to have been hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; for that had been to have confeſt the whole Catholique Church to be hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ſo utterly extinct, which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; neither was there ever any <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> that confeſt, the whole Dioceſſe, or Sea of Rome was ever hereticall; ſo that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37695:9"/>
whether by <hi>Rome,</hi> you mean the particular Church of Rome, or the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church,</hi> your aſſertion is moſt impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and falſe, neither have you nam'd any one man that confeſt it.</p>
            <p>10. But perchance the Doctor intended theſe argunents for light skirmiſhes onely, and ha's reſerv'd his main force and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for his laſt affault, and with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve hopes to obtain a ſignall victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Let us then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter it, and try what force it brings with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Rome</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>be the Catholique Church, if any thing be amiſſe in any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, the fault is Hers, and She ought to mend it; therefore</hi> Rome <hi>is not the Catholike Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a wretched conſequence is this? certainly the Doctor ha's forgot all his <hi>Logick,</hi> or found out ſome new, which no body knows beſides himſelf; by the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idiculous conſequence I will prove that the Parliament of England was never the Supreme Power of England; Thus.</p>
            <p>If the Parliament of England were the Supreme Power, if any thing were amiſſe in any particular, the fault was in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and it ought to have mended it; therefore the Parliament of England was
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37695:10"/>
never the Supreme Power of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding your ridiculous conſequence, I will grant your concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as being nothing to the purpoſe; for your concluſion ſhould have been this; <hi>therefore the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and theſe in communion with her, are not the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church.</hi> And if we examine the ſequell of the <hi>Antecedent,</hi> we ſhall find it as ridiculous as the whole conſequence; for why ſhould the church be blam'd for any thing that is a miſſe in any particular point of doctrine, or diſcipline, and that in any particular church, or member of the Church Catholike? (for by [particular], you muſt mean one of thoſe, but which I know not) <hi>Arius</hi> denied an high point of Catholike Faith, and many of the Eaſtern church would not obſerve <hi>Eaſter-day,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtolique cuſtom of the Catholike Church, but I cannot ſee, why the blaſphemy of the one, or the Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of the other ſhould be imputed to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with her, which is the Catholique Church; ſhe uſed all her power and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to reclaim both, and when heretikes have forſaken her faith, or ſchiſmatiques her communion, ſhe ha's always uſed that power and authority wherewith God ha's
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37695:10"/>
inveſted her, to cauſe them to return to their faith and obedience, but if the ſchiſmatike ſhall perſiſt in his ſchiſm, or the hererique in his hereſie, the fault is in them, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the church; that you, Doctor, moſt obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately continue in your hereſie, the fault is yours, not the churches, ſhe ha's imployed her utmoſt endeavours to reclaim you, and therefore cannot juſtly be blamed for your hereſie or ſchiſme; but if any particular Biſhops or Paſtors have been negligent in reclaiming heretiques or ſchiſmatiques, they muſt anſwer for it, ſtill the church is blameleſſe.</p>
            <p>10. In the next place the Doctor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes concerning the Viſibility of the Catholique Church, which he grants to have been alwayes viſible, both in, and from the time of the Apoſtles to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, but he will not grant it alwayes viſible in one and the ſame place, no not to <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, nor to every eye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Doctor will be alwayes proving that which was never queſtion'd, but by his leave, the Catholique Church ha's been alwayes viſible at <hi>Rome,</hi> even from its firſt converſion to the Chriſtian Faith, to this preſent day, as far as the Catholique Church can be viſible in any particular branch or member; but who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37695:11"/>
ſaid or thought, that the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church was at any time viſible at <hi>Rome?</hi> that City, we know, was never ſo capacious, as to be able to contain all the Catholikes that have been for theſe many ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, living at the ſame time in <hi>Europe, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> and <hi>Africa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>11. And that it ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not been alwayes viſible to every eye, (who ever ſaid it was?) he endeavours to prove, becauſe <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaw not the church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his time, and becauſe the church was not viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to many in the days of <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If that church were ſometimes ſo obſcured, that it might be inviſible to many, nay, to moſt of that Nation (for it could not be, and be totally obſcured, and inviſible to all eys) yet, good Doctor, you cannot deny, but that the church was apparently viſible, both before and after <hi>Elijah,</hi> before and after <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> before and after <hi>Ahaz,</hi> before and after <hi>Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> but neither you, nor all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in the world can ſhew, that at any time, not only for theſe 1100. yeares laſt paſt, but for 1600. years, even from S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> to theſe our dayes, there was any Catholique Church diſtinct from the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in communion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37695:11"/>
with her, whereas that church ha's beene moſt perſpicuouſly and apparently viſible to the world in all ages, ſince the Apoſtles time to this preſent time: Beſides, that the Catholike Church ſhould be viſible in times of hotteſt perſecution, and ſo viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that we can even at this day point at it, and that afterwards, when it was more glorious, it ſhould become inviſible to all eyes (as that church muſt be which was diſtinct from the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe in communion with her) and that for ſo many hundred yeares, tranſcends any mans underſtanding, but D. <hi>Boughens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>12. <hi>It is more then probable</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that there were in this very Iſland 7000. ſoules that were not tainted with Popiſh errours;</hi> but he brings not ſo much as a probable argument for it: By <hi>Popiſh Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi> he means the antient doctrine of the <hi>Roman Catholike Church;</hi> but it is moſt improbable, that there were ſo many as ſeven (beſides ſuch as were condemn'd for Heretikes, and confeſt to be ſuch, even by Proteſtants themſelves) that before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> Apoſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie were ſeparated from the Roman church, for there was not ſo much as one man or woman that followed <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> or any other Proteſtant whatſoever in their new Doctrine, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac't
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37695:12"/>
their new Reformation, as you call it, but had been before a profeſt <hi>Roman Catholike.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>13. <hi>It is enough for us</hi> (ſayes the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor) <hi>to prove them to be errours, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scripture, and the received ſenſe of the antient church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For ſhame, Doctor, recall your words, I am ſure that this ſpeech muſt proceed from much impudence or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, they were never yet prov'd to be errors againſt Scripture, ſome indeed have barkt againſt Gods church, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med her faith and doctrine, (as you have done in this Pamphlet) wreſting the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to their damnable purpoſes; and I am ſure, that of all men you will never be able to prove them ſo: But what can be more apparent to the world, then that all Antiquity confirms the doctrine of the Roman church, and condemns yours.</p>
            <p>14. That which you ſay concerning the Popes, <hi>Liberius, Honorius,</hi> and <hi>Jo.</hi> 22. ſhall be anſwer'd hereafter in a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place.</p>
            <p>15. But the Doctor is ſure, <hi>that he ha's manifeſted, that the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe particular churches in her communion, are not, cannot be the</hi> Catholike Church.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37695:12"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Indeed he ha's made it ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that no body can ſee it; for if this concluſion [<hi>The</hi> church <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe particular churches in her communion, are not, cannot be the Catholike Church</hi>] be either expreſly, or implicitly in any thing that he ha's ſaid before, I will then lay down the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dgells, and never lift up my hand more againſt D. <hi>Boughen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>16. In his following diſcourſe, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſe the Doctor ſeems to ſay more then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he ſaid before, <hi>viz. That the</hi> church <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe in communion with her, might be a Catholike, but not the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, a part, but not the whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But, good Doctor, ſaying is one thing, and manifeſting another; this muſt not be beg'd, but prov'd; all that he ſaid before was, that <hi>Rome</hi> was a particular church, and this too was but only ſaid, not prov'd at all; and now he (at leaſt) ſeems to draw neerer to the queſtion, and ſay, <hi>that the</hi> church <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular churches in her communion, are but a part of the Catholike Church;</hi> and that therefore the Catholike Church is of a larger extent, and comprehends within her bounds more churches then thoſe only that are in communion with the church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37695:13"/>This is eaſily ſaid, but where are your proofs? where is your Scripture for it? or where is your authority of Fathers or Councells for it? can you, or any man elſe ſhew, that at any time, between the times of the Apoſtles, and <hi>Luthers</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie, there was any particular church di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from the church of Rome, and thoſe in communion with her, and yet acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged either by the church of Rome, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in communion with her, or by any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Father, or any Catholique Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, to be a true member of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like church? if this cannot be ſhown (as I am moſt certain it cannot) why ſhould we take it upon your word, <hi>that the</hi> church <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>and thoſe in communion with her, is not the Catholike Church, but a part only thereof?</hi> was there ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular church (not in communion with the church of Rome) that ſent her Biſhops and Prelats to any General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, wherein the whole Catholike Church was repreſented? or did ever any General Councell receive Biſhops, or permit them to ſit and vote there, that were ſent from any ſuch church, or that would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their ſubjection to the Biſhop of Rome, as the common Paſtor, and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble head of Gods church? 'tis very ſtrange,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37695:13"/>
that there ſhould be whole churches, whole countryes and Nations, all true members of the Catholike Church, and ſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that were not in communion with the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged any ſubjection to the Sea or Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> and yet that there ſhould be no Records thereof, that all theſe ſhould be inviſible to the world for theſe 1600. yeares together. Theſe are ſtrong arguments againſt you, Doctor, what arguments you will hereafter bring for your ſelfe, I know not, but as yet, I am ſure, you have brought none at all.</p>
            <p>17. I commend your wiſdome in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the words of thoſe Canons by you cited. Sect. 10. for you plainly perceived that they made nothing for you. That ſixth canon of the <hi>Councel of Nice,</hi> which ſeems moſt to ſtrengthen your cauſe, and ha's been ſo often objected by your party, and ſo often anſwer'd, ha's been prov'd upon diligent examination, to make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt you, as appeares plainly: <hi>Concil. Calc. Act.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>18. But the Doctor is much ſcandaliz'd at <hi>the maiming of the Lords Supper; ſo that if there were no other cauſe then that, he could not communicate with the Church of Rome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Sect. 11. It ſeems, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37695:14"/>
               <hi>Boughen</hi> cannot content himſelf with that, wherewith the good <hi>Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> were all ſatisfied. They could be contented to carry the <hi>bleſſed Sacrament</hi> to their houſes, and reſerve it there for times of neceſſity under one <hi>Species.</hi> They thought it ſufficient to miniſter it to their ſick under the Species of Bread onely, to their children (when that by ſome was thought neceſſary) under the Species of Wine onely, but the Doctor will have both, or none. None of the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor the moſt learned of all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians, could ever find it in Scripture, that Chriſt ordained the bleſſed Sacrament to be given in both kinds to all ſorts of people; but Doctor <hi>Boughen</hi> is ſo quick-ſighted, that he ha's diſcover'd that which the whole church for 1500. yeares together could not find out.</p>
            <p>19. But, good Doctor, how do we rob the Laity of Chriſts bloud? if thoſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Bread and Wine be after Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, truly, really, and ſubſtantially chang'd into the body and blood of our bleſſed Saviour? then thoſe that receive his body, receive his blood alſo; for whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever communicates under one Species on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, receives both the body and bloud: And if there be no ſuch change (as I am ſure,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37695:14"/>
according to your doctrine, there is not) then we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ob them, at the moſt, but of the ſign or figure of Chriſts blood; neither indeed is it in the power of the Prieſt, or church to rob them of that; for if the cup after conſecration be but a bare ſign or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Chriſts blood, ſtill retaining its former nature and ſubſtance of wine, then may any one, in ſpight of the Prieſt or church, take a cup of wine, when and where he pleaſe, and make it to himſelfe a ſign of Chriſts blood, and ſo it may be to him as perfect a Sacrament, as if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it from the hands of the Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Perchance you will ſay, it is not a ſigne but by vertue of Conſecration: This may be eaſily ſaid, but can you prove it out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scripture, which you make the ſole rule of your Faith? If you can, then will I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to your opinion, if not, (as I am moſt certain you cannot) then according to your owne Principle, neither you, nor I, nor any man elſe is bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it.</p>
            <p>20. But here I meet with two Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties out of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> to prove, that none can be fit for Martyrdome, that commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate not under the Species of Wine as well as of Bread: certainly the Doctor (to ſay no worſe) miſunderſtands <hi>S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37695:15"/>
for he was too great a Scholar to maintaine ſo falſe and ridiculous a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; his words in the firſt place cited by the Doctor, are theſe, <hi>Quomodo ad Martyrii p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>culum idoneos facimus, ſi non eos ad bibendum priùs in Eccleſia poculum Domini jure communicationis admitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus?</hi> Cypr. li. 1. Epiſt. 2.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that all this Father intends in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Cornelius,</hi> is; to deſire the Pope, that thoſe, who for fear of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution had fallen from their faith, might upon their repentance and reconciliation to the church be admitted to the holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, that by the vertue and power of that Sacrament they might be the better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to encounter with, and overcome a new perſecution. There is not ſo much as one word in the whole Epiſtle concerning the inſufficiency of communicating under one Species onely, or the neceſſity of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating under both, thoſe words [<hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum Domini</hi>] the cup of our Lord, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying there the bleſſed Sacrament in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, in alluſion to the former words, [<hi>Poculum Martyrii</hi>] the cup of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: and this will moſt plainly appeare to any one that ſhall impartially <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ead that Epiſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; all that can poſſibly be proved out of thoſe words, is, that in ſome places
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37695:15"/>
in or about the time of <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> the Laity we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> admitted to communicate under both kinds, which no Catholike ever denied or queſtion'd; and that it was a cuſtome even in S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> time to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Communion in one kind one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may eaſily be prov'd from thoſe two miracles recorded by the ſame Father, <hi>Serm. de Lapſis.</hi> to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>The other place cited out of S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> has theſe words, <hi>Quomodo poſſumus propter Chriſtum ſanguinem fundere, qui ſanguin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſti crubeſcimus bibere?</hi> Lib. 2. Ep. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe words I confeſſe are S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians,</hi> but they are leſſe to the purpoſe then the former, as I ſhall inſtantly make it appear.</p>
            <p>There were certain Heretikes in S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians</hi> time, who contrary to our bleſſed Saviours inſtitution (as this Father ſayes) would conſecrate in wine alone, without any mixture of water; and others who would conſecrate in water alone, without wine: againſt theſe latter S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends theſe words cited, ſaying, that ſuch drink not the bloud of Chriſt, ſince water cannot by vertue of conſecration, be chang'd into the bloud of Chriſt, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the defect of wine, which is the true
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37695:16"/>
matter of the Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rament, and therefore could not have the power and efficacy of the Sacrament to enable men to overcome thoſe great difficulties and temptations of perſecution, and to lay down their lives for the faith of Chriſt. But there is not one word in that whole Epiſtle concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing receiving the Sacrament under one or both Species.</p>
            <p>21. Now to paſſe by divers impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and ſuch things as have beene already anſwer'd, let us come to the Doctors Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-argument, (for doubtleſſe he eſteemes it ſo, otherwiſe he would not ſo much have inſiſted upon it, and repeated it ſo often) which to ſet forth in its full luſtre, he has at laſt adventur'd on this <hi>Syllogiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ye (the Church of Rome) have at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time denied Jeſus Christ to be the true God, and eternal life, ye were at that time no church, but an Anti-chriſtian Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But this did</hi> Marcellinus, <hi>and</hi> Liberius, <hi>and Jo. 22. all Biſhops of Rome.</hi> Ergo; <hi>In thoſe times ye were no church, but an Anti-chriſtian Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What an Anti-chriſtian Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm is here? Anti-chriſt ha's not more heads, then this Syllogiſm ha's termes. But let us be once more favourable to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37695:16"/>
and help him to ſpeak ſenſe; he means well, thohgh he ha's forgot his Logick: all then that I can make of it, is this.</p>
            <p>There was a time when <hi>Rome,</hi> and all thoſe in communion with her, were no church at all, but an <hi>Anti-chriſtian Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the Catholike Church, which never failed, muſt be diſtinct from the Church of Rome, and all thoſe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with her.</p>
            <p>This I confeſſe is a pretty good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, but the Doctor may thank me for it: Well then, not to queſtion the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, we deny the antecedent which is prov'd thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marcellinus</hi> and <hi>Liberius,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o.</hi> 22. all Biſhops of Rome, denied Jeſus Chriſt to be the true God, and eternall life. <hi>Ergo:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a time when the Church of Rome, and thoſe in communion with her were no church, but an anti-chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Synagogue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is your conſequence, Doctor, not mine. Would not you have laughed at me, or any man, that ſhould have conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the whole church of England to have been formealy heroticall and ſchiſmaticall, becauſe the King, or <hi>Arch biſhop of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37695:17"/>
(one whereof you acknowledged head of your pretended Church) was He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical or Schiſmatical? Muſt every Church ſtand or fall with its <hi>Biſhop?</hi> Muſt the particular members of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> neceſſarily forſake their faith, if her <hi>Biſhop</hi> fall into Herefie, or Idolatry? You con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. 10. that there was a viſible true Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> in thoſe dayes, when both their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>High Preiſt</hi> had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the true God, and committed Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and muſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly periſh, if her <hi>Biſhop</hi> forſake his faith? Shall the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> have a prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative above the Church of <hi>Christ?</hi> This is <hi>Logick</hi> I underſtand not.</p>
            <p>22. And though this might ſerve for a full and ſatisfactory anſwer, to any judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and impartial Reader; yet ſince I find divers good <hi>Popes</hi> falſly charged with He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie and Idolatry, I ſhall endeavour, <hi>Ex ſuperabundanti,</hi> to vindicate them from thoſe foul aſperſions, and ſo deſtroy the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent,</hi> as well as the <hi>Conſequence,</hi> by ſhewing, the <hi>Doctor</hi> is here as much out in his <hi>History,</hi> as he was before in his <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>22. Firſt then, <hi>Pope Liberius</hi> is accus'd of <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> but falſly; for he never ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to that damnable Hereſie, never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37695:17"/>
taught, or maintained it. He ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed only to the baniſhment of S. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> to which the Emperor <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'t and compel'd him by torments; as St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf teſtifies in both his <hi>Apologies,</hi> where he clearly acquits him of Hereſie. And if St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in an other place, and St. <hi>Hierom</hi> charge him with ſubſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ibing to <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> it is to be underſtood, <hi>interpretative</hi> only; in that he ſubſcribed to S. <hi>Athanaſiuſ</hi>'s baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was procur'd by the <hi>Arrians;</hi> and externally communicated with ſome <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhops: eſpecially ſince not only thoſe ancient Authors <hi>Socrates,</hi> lib 2. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cief. Hiſt. <hi>c. 29. Sozomen.</hi> lib. 4. <hi>c. 10. Theodoret,</hi> lib. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16, 17. but alſo S. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> himſelf in the fore-cited places te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies, that he was no Heretique, and that he did nothing in compliance with the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> but what he was compell'd unto by a tedious baniſhment, and force of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And that all <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould ſide with this Pope in that Hereſie, as you afterwards charge them, (<hi>Sect.</hi> 23.) is moſt notoriouſly falſe, ſpoken <hi>gratis,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any authority, or ground whatſoever.</p>
            <p>23. The ſecond <hi>Pope</hi> that ſtands charg'd with <hi>Hereſie</hi> is <hi>Honorius:</hi> but what his he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie was, the Doctor declares not. Tis true,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37695:18"/>
ſome Heretiques have charg'd this <hi>Pope</hi> (upon what ground I know not) with joyning with the <hi>Monothelites</hi> in their he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie: but it cannot appear, that ever he held or taught that Hereſie, either publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or privatly. His errors were at the moſt but conjectured by ſome private Letters, which after his death were publiſhed in his name. But that in his life time he renounc't that Hereſie, appears, <hi>Epiſt. Honor. ad Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium. Act. 13. ſext. Synod.</hi> Yet ſuppoſe <hi>Honorius</hi> had erred; what was that to the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> ſhe notwithſtanding might be free from error. And that <hi>de facto,</hi> ſhe was free, and perſecuted that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, <hi>Pirrhus</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> being at her ſuit baniſh't by <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raclius</hi> the Emperor, appears plainly by <hi>Platina,</hi> in <hi>Honor.</hi> 1. and <hi>Sabellicus</hi> Aenead. 8. lib 6.</p>
            <p>24. In the next place comes in <hi>Zepheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> charg'd with <hi>Montaniſm;</hi> but moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly. He was no <hi>Montaniſt;</hi> only out of a candid and peaceable diſpoſition, he endeavoured to make peace between the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques</hi> and the <hi>Montaniſts;</hi> and this was all his Hereſie. That plrce of <hi>Lyra</hi> by you cited, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. makes rather againſt you then for you. He ſayes there, that ſome <hi>Popes</hi> have <hi>Apoſtatiz'd,</hi> and thence concludes, that the Church depends not on
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37695:18"/>
any particular mans perſon, but conſiſts in thoſe that profeſs the true faith of Chriſt. He ſees not your conſequence; That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> falls into Hereſie, therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical; but maintains the contrary.</p>
            <p>25. But behold <hi>Marcellinus</hi> an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who denyed Chriſt, and offred ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to Idols. <hi>Anſw.</hi> So alſo did S. <hi>Peter</hi> deny his Maſter. <hi>Marcellinus</hi> externally denyed Chriſt for fear of torments; ſo did St. <hi>Peter</hi> for fear of the <hi>Jews:</hi> yet they both confeſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> in their hearts, though they both grievouſly ſinned in their exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal denying of him: But as S. <hi>Peter</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, and afterward became a glorious Martyr; ſo likewiſe did this bleſſed <hi>Pope</hi> follow S. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter,</hi> both in his Repentance and Martyrdom.</p>
            <p>But what is this to the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Did all the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> deny <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe S. <hi>Peter</hi> denyed him? I ſuppoſe, no man of reaſon will ſay ſo; and if not, why ſhould the whole Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be ſaid to forſake her faith, becauſe her <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> for fear of torments denyed <hi>Chriſt</hi> in ſome ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ior action, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> had done before him by oaths, and execrations? Perchance, you will ſay, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> was not as truly chief of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and head
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37695:19"/>
of that Church. which was then in being, when he denyed his Maſter, as <hi>Marcellinus</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> To this I anſwer, that our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> had then founded his Church, <hi>viz.</hi> the night before S. <hi>Peters</hi> denial; when he gave an end to the <hi>legal types</hi> and <hi>ceremonies,</hi> and inſtituted the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> of his <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious body</hi> and <hi>bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church thus founded, S. <hi>Peter</hi> muſt neceſſarily be the <hi>head</hi> thereof, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently chief of all the <hi>Apostles,</hi> unleſs you will deny the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to be part of that Church, which was then in being. And he that ſhall deny S. <hi>Peter</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, gives <hi>Chriſt</hi> the lye; who formerly had made that promiſe to <hi>S. Peter</hi> in plain and expreſs words, Matth. 16. 18. <hi>Thou ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a rock, and up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n this rock will I build my Church. Chriſt</hi> ſaid not; thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and upon this <hi>Rock</hi> will I build my Church; as you falſly tranſlate, to deceive the world; but, <hi>Thou art Cephas,</hi> (which in the Syrian language, which our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> then ſpake, ſignifies a <hi>Rock; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Cephas</hi> (that is, <hi>this Rock</hi>) will I build my Church.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> uſed not two diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent words, as you would make the world believe, as [<hi>Peter</hi>] in one place; and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37695:19"/>
[<hi>Rock</hi>] in the other; but in both places uſed the word (<hi>Cephas</hi>) which ſignifies a <hi>Rock,</hi> that being the name which Chriſt gave to <hi>Peter</hi> when he firſt call'd him. And though the <hi>Catholike Tranſlaters</hi> of the New <hi>Teſtament,</hi> who profeſs to follow exactly the vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> Edition, as being more authentick, then any <hi>Greek</hi> Copy now extant in the world, have tranſlated that place, as you do, viz. <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> &amp;c. yet have they dealt more ingeniouſly with the world, in advertiſing, that the word [<hi>Peter</hi>] ſignifies a <hi>Rock;</hi> and that our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> uſed not two, but one and the ſame word [<hi>Cephas,</hi>] which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a <hi>Rock,</hi> in that promiſe made to S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> whereas you, though profeſſing to follow the <hi>Original,</hi> yet when it makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you forſake it, and follow the <hi>Latin;</hi> and when that makes againſt you, then you pretend to follow the <hi>Original.</hi> Thus you will alwayes have a ſhift to delude the world, and your own ſouls; for had you in that place followed the <hi>Original,</hi> you ſhould have tranſlated it, [<hi>Thou art a Rock,</hi>] not [<hi>Thou art Peter:</hi>] beſides in the <hi>Greek</hi> the words are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies a <hi>Rock,</hi> as ruly, and as properly as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>So then Chriſt founded his Church on
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37695:20"/>
S. <hi>Peter</hi> as a <hi>Rock,</hi> as the very connexion of the words demonſtrate: For in theſe words of our bleſſed Saviour [<hi>I ſay unto thee</hi> (Peter,) <hi>thou art a Rock, and upon this Rock will I build my Church.</hi>] Can any reaſonable man imagine, that by thoſe words [<hi>This Rock</hi>] Chriſt meant any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rock then that whereof he made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the words immediately preceding, viz. <hi>Thou art a Rock?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is then moſt apparent that Chriſt built his Church on S. <hi>Peters</hi> perſon, at leaſt, as to the Diſcipline and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, and conſequently upon his Succeſſors. For if our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> knew that his Church, even in her very infancy, when the Apoſtles themſelves inſpired with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> where a great part thereof would ſtand in need of ſome ſupreme <hi>Head</hi> and Governour; certainly he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw, that when his Church ſhould be more ample, and numerous, and more ſubject to diviſions and factions, it would ſtand in far greater need of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Head,</hi> wherein all particular Churches, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof might be united; and therefore would not leave it without ſome <hi>common Paſtor</hi> to guide and direct it. And I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to take notice <hi>Doctor,</hi> that herein all the Fathers, both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37695:20"/>
and modern unanimouſly agree; and that this common and ſupreme Paſtor of <hi>Chriſts Church</hi> ever was, and ever muſt be S. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor, who hithet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o (ever ſince S. <hi>Peter</hi> plac't his Chair there) has been the biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and for ought we know, ever will be till the end of the world. And this thoſe very Authors, <hi>Stella</hi> and <hi>Lyra,</hi> whom you have cited for your ſelf, will plainly tell you, even in thoſe very places which you have cited.</p>
            <p>Beſides, who ever confirm'd the acts of any lawful General Councel, but the Pope? In his abſence had he not his <hi>Delegates,</hi> who ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in the ſupreme place of the Councel, though they were not alwayes Biſhops, and that even in the <hi>Eaſterne Church?</hi> I could be more copious in this point, but I here intend a reply only, not a Treatiſe of <hi>Controverſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>26. I come now to Pope <hi>John</hi> 22. who ſtands charg'd with a ſtrange and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Hereſie, viz. for affirming, that <hi>God the Son</hi> is greater then <hi>God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and <hi>Stella's</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is produc't to prove it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I confeſs <hi>Stella</hi> has accus'd him of it, but I muſt be bold to exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pt againſt his authority and teſtimony in this matter of fact; for it cannot appear that <hi>Stella</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:37695:21"/>
ſpake this upon any juſt ground, or proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; for no man beſides <hi>Stella,</hi> either <hi>Catholique,</hi> or <hi>Heretique</hi> (that I could ever yet read or hear of) ever charg'd Pope <hi>John</hi> 22. with that blaſphemy: 'tis true, ſome Heretiques, and amongſt the reſt <hi>Calvin (Juſt. li. 4. c.</hi> 7. Sect. 28.) have charged this Pope, for affirming, that the ſouls of men were mortal, but moſt injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, for he never taught, nor held the mortality of the ſoul; all that he held con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the opinion of the world was, That the ſouls of the Juſt ſhould not ſee God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> This opinion was far from Hereſie, the Church never having defin'd the contrary, and divers ancient Catholique Fathers being of the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; neither did he ever abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that opinion, as an unqueſtionable truth. For as <hi>Jo. Villanus.</hi> Hiſior. li. 11. cap. 19. reports, the day before his death he declar'd, that he never had any intent to define it, and that whenſoever he diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of it, his end was to find out the truth, and added withall, that he held the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion to be more probable, and I am ſure it is moſt improbable, that <hi>Ockam</hi> his bitter enemy ſhould charge him with this, and <hi>Calvin</hi> with the other, and yet neither of theſe ſhould make any mention of that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37695:21"/>
blaſphemous Hereſie which D. <hi>Boughen</hi> one of <hi>Stella</hi> layes to his charge; if either he had been guilty, or they could have found any probable argument, or colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ground, that he might be guilty of that horrid blaſphemy: but ſuppoſe this had been true, as it is far from all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of truth, what is this to the purpoſe? What if <hi>Liberius, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcellinus,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> 22. all <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> had their private errors? what is all this to the Church of Rome? your Intelligencer <hi>Stella</hi> (even in that place by you cited) will tell you, they erred as private perſons only, not as biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> they never decreed, nor defin'd Hereſie; they never commanded any heretical Doctrine to be receiv'd as a divine truth by the whole Church: They might fall into errors; ſo likewiſe did <hi>Peter,</hi> (as <hi>Stella</hi> ſayes) even after <hi>Chriſt</hi> had prayed for him, that his Faith ſhould not fail. But I ſuppoſe no man will be ſo unreaſonable, or blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, as to ſay, <hi>Peters</hi> Faith failed, after Chriſt had prayed that it ſhould not fail, though externally for fear of the Jews he denied it: <hi>Peter</hi> then denied his Faith, what was this to the other <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Diſciples? <hi>Liberius, Marcellinus,</hi> and Pope <hi>John</hi> 22. had their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37695:22"/>
errors, what was this to the Church of Rome? had you read <hi>Stella</hi> but a very few lines further, you would have found ſmall incouragement to have cited his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for your opinion; for though he ſeems in ſome ſenſe to grant your <hi>Minor Propoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion</hi> (as you call it Sect. 18.) in your misſh pen Syllogiſm, Sect. 17. viz. <hi>That Liberius, Marcellinus,</hi> and <hi>Iohn 22. erred in Faith,</hi> yet he there plainly denies your concluſion, viz. <hi>That therefore in their times the Church of Rome became no Church, but was an Anti-chriſtian Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue:</hi> His words in <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. 31. the very place by you cited, are theſe, <hi>Eccleſia enim Autiochena, Alexandrina, &amp; Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politana, ſaepe defecerunt à fide; Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia verò Romana nunquam defecil; quia Chriſtus ait Petro; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ravi pro te, ut uon deficiat fides tua. The Church</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of Antioch, Alexandria, and Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, have often fallen from their faith, but the Church of Rome never fell from her faith, becauſe Chriſt ſaid to</hi> Peter, <hi>I have prayed for thee, that thy Faith fail not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee <hi>Doctor</hi> what a plain teſtimony here is againſt you, out of the ſame <hi>Author</hi> which you have cited for you: <hi>Stella</hi> was not ſo ſharp-ſighted as to ſee your conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37695:22"/>
viz. <hi>That beauſe Marcellinus, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius, and John 22. had fallen from the true faith, therefore the Church of Rome had forſaken her faith;</hi> but the contrary he maintains exprefly, viz. <hi>That although Liberius, Marccllinus, and John 22. all Popes of Rome, denied the true Faith, yet the Church of Rome never failed, or fell from her faith:</hi> He could not draw your <hi>Concluſion</hi> from ſuch <hi>Premiſes</hi> as yours are; and yet doubtleſs he knew a Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm, and a rational conſequence as well as you.</p>
            <p>27. But why ſhould <hi>Vigilius</hi> be an <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tychian?</hi> was it becauſe out of reverence and reſpect to the Councel of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> he could not be induc't, neither by the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, nor threatnings of the Emperour, to repeal an <hi>Act</hi> of that <hi>Councel,</hi> in condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe <hi>Tria Capitula,</hi> which the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ccl had receiv'd as Orthodox, nothing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the Hereſie, either of <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> or <hi>Eutyches,</hi> one whereof was the Epiſtle of <hi>Ibas,</hi> who publiquely in the Councel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc't the Hereſies, both of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and <hi>Eutyches;</hi> another, the writings of <hi>Theodoret</hi> againſt <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> for which <hi>Theodoret</hi> had formerly been depos'd by the <hi>Eutychian</hi> Faction in that <hi>Latrocinal</hi> Councel at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37695:23"/>
by the Catholiques? I confeſs this is a very ſtrong argument, that he was no <hi>Eutychian:</hi> but that he was one, you only ſay it, you alledg no reaſon, you cite no authority nor teſtimony, but that of <hi>Lyra,</hi> whom I cannot find making any mention at all in the place by you cited in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. either of this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilius,</hi> or of any other Pope whatſoever, only in general terms he ſayes, That ſome Popes have apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, which is nothing to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>28. To the Queſtion, where your Church was before the <hi>Reformation,</hi> Sect. 19. (I ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> uſed not the word [<hi>Reformation</hi>] but by it, I conceive, you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean, your ſeparation from the <hi>Roman Church</hi>) To this Queſtion, you ſay, it was anſwered; <hi>In the Catholique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I confeſs the anſwer is moſt true, when you were a Church, you were in the <hi>Catholique Church;</hi> ſo alſo were formerly the <hi>Arrians, Macedonians, Pelagians, Neſtorians, Entychians, Donatiſts, &amp;c.</hi> all theſe before their reſpective <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that is, before they fell into Hereſie and Schiſm, were within the walls of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church; before their ſeparation, they were all in communion with the Church of Rome, and therefore true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the <hi>Church Catholique;</hi> ſo likewiſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37695:23"/>
were you; and as the <hi>Arians, &amp;c.</hi> by forſaking the communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and oppoſing her doctine and faith, cut themſelves off from the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> and ſo ceaſt to be members thereof, even ſo have you now ceaſt to be any Church at all, by ſeparating your ſelves from your <hi>Mother Church,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with whom you had been in communion for the ſpace of almoſt a thouſand years together, even from the firſt converſion of this Nation to the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> by S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> to K. <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's apoſtoſie.</p>
            <p>19. <hi>Before the Reformation</hi> (you ſay) <hi>we communicated with Rome, and ſince we have not; that's no fault of ours, ye will not ſuffer us to communicate with you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we communicate with your errors?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is very fine: who, I pray, ſhal judg of thoſe <hi>errors? Chriſt</hi> has made his Church Judg of your errours? what Heretiques ever were there in the world, that did not, or might not have us'd the ſame Plea for their ſeparation from Gods Church? Was there ever any particular Church that preſum'd to cenſme the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Catholique Church? Or was it not exceſſive pride, if not madneſs in you, to think that you were wiſer then the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37695:24"/>
whole Chriſtian world had been for 1500. years before you? Can you ſhew, that in any age ſince the Apoſtlos, the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> held and taught your doctrine? can you prove that ever any particular Church, or Nation, taught or maintain'd the ſame? nay, I will go further; can you produce any one man, in any age from <hi>Chriſts Paſſion</hi> to <hi>Luthers Apoſtaſia,</hi> let him be of the <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Laity,</hi> either <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique,</hi> or <hi>Heretique,</hi> that agreed with you in all points of your Faith and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, wherein you now diſſent from the <hi>Church of Rome?</hi> if you cannot, methinks your ſelves ſhould condemn your ſelves for ſeparating from that <hi>Church;</hi> in whoſe Faith and communion all your Anceſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for ſo many ages liv'd and died, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing a new Doctrine (and that out of your owne judgement and fancy onely) for which you have neither preſident nor authority.</p>
            <p>30. And yet I muſt confeſs that your Religion is not altogether now, it is a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for the moſt part, patcht up of old condemned Hereſies, though there were never any Heretiques before <hi>Luther,</hi> that held all your Doctrine. I know, your or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary pretence is to appeal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o, and to be judg'd by the <hi>Scripture:</hi> but do you not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37695:24"/>
firſt make your ſelves Judges of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture? do you not impoſe new ſenſes and interpretations on Gods holy Word, ſuch as were never heard of before your <hi>Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie?</hi> do you not, againſt all reaſon, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret plain places of Scripture by obſcure, rather then the obſcure by the plain? and when by your corrupt <hi>tranſlations,</hi> falſe <hi>gloſſes,</hi> and new <hi>interpretations,</hi> you have made the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeak what you pleaſe, then you cry out, <hi>The Scripture has given ſentence for you againſt the Church of Rome.</hi> I confeſs, ſince you have made your ſelves Maſters of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> you were very unwiſe, if you would not make him ſpeak as you would have him; you have uſurped a power, that we dare not chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge; we tremble at that fearful <hi>curſe</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc't by S. <hi>Paul (Gal.1.)</hi> againſt all thoſe that ſhall teach new Doctrines: We hearken to, not conſure the Church: We imbrace her doctrine, not charge her with errours. But I would ask any reaſonable man (though there were no Obligation, yet) whether it were not more prudential for a man to build his ſalvation on the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the whole Church, then of ſome particular perſons, not altogether agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongſt themſelves, and diſagreeing from the whole world beſides; or whether
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37695:25"/>
it were not more reaſonable to imbrace the doctrines and interpretations of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> that were univerſally receiv'd by the whole Church for 1500. years, then thoſe new doctrines and interpretations of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and his followers. You confeſs, that before your <hi>Reformation</hi> (as you call it) you communicated with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> How came you to find that the Church wanted a Reformation, and that in Doctrine? (for in matters of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and manners you might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd your ſelves, and yet ſtill have been in communion with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) How came you to diſcover thoſe errors, which none in the whole Chriſtian world beſides your ſelves could perceive? before your ſeparation there was no particular branch or member of the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> but was in communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> How then came you to ſee that light, which none beſides your ſelves could ſee? Was all the world beſides you blind? Had you only the <hi>Scripture?</hi> Or could you only interpret them? But why do I ſpeak of you, as of a company or multitude? For though Time has now made the difference to be between the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally it was between <hi>Luther</hi> and the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37695:25"/>
whole Church; you in <hi>England,</hi> as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> are but <hi>Luthers</hi> followers. The Church then went one way, and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> another; and you very wiſely have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the whole Church, and followed <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Do but examine this according to the principles of common prudence, and then tell me, <hi>Doctor,</hi> whether you have done diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly. You have forſaken the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, and followed one man; who neither had, nor pretended to any extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary calling. He never wrought miracle in confirmation of his new Doctrines; or to manifeſt to the world that <hi>God</hi> had revealed that Truth unto him, which for many ages had been totally obſcur'd, and unknown to the world. It is then your fault now, that you communicate not with the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> ſince it was your fault formerly that you forſook her, to follow one man. If you will forſake that ſingle Apoſtate, and return to your faith and obedience, you ſhall ſoon be receiv'd; the Churches armes are alwayes open to imbrace you.</p>
            <p>Before your pretended <hi>Reformation</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your own confeſſion, <hi>Sect.</hi> 19) you communicated with <hi>Rome;</hi> that is, you acknowledged your ſubjection to the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> You confeſt the Biſhop thereof to be the ſupream viſible
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37695:26"/>
               <hi>Head</hi> of Chriſts Church, appointed by Chriſt himſelf to be ſo; as St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor. For no particular Church, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ever was, or could be in communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that denied, or queſtioned this Doctrine, or that refuſed to yeeld obedience to the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Mother</hi> of all Churches, and to the Biſhop thereof as Chriſts <hi>Vicar Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> on Earth. How then came you (in <hi>England</hi>) to find out that at laſt, which your Anceſtors for almoſt 1000. years could not diſcover? They all even from the firſt converſion of this Nation to the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> by St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> to K. <hi>Hen.</hi> eights <hi>Defection,</hi> were ſubject to the <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to the Biſhop thereof, as Chriſts immediate <hi>Vicar,</hi> and under him, the ſupream <hi>head</hi> of the <hi>Catholike Church.</hi> How come you to be wiſer then all your fore-fathers, and the whole world b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſides? Can it be reaſonably ſuppoſed, that thoſe great <hi>Patriarchs</hi> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt,</hi> the <hi>Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiech,</hi> &amp;c. with all the Biſhops of <hi>Aſia, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> ſhould profeſs and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelves ſubject to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> had they not thought, that his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and Juriſdiction over the whole <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church</hi> had been by Chriſts eſpecial
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37695:26"/>
appointment and commiſſion? What co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable plea then can you alleadge for your ſeparation?</p>
            <p>31. But I perceive the <hi>Doctor</hi> is flying to his old fallacy, in taking for granted, or rather indeed downright begging, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can be no more then a particular branch or member of the Church <hi>Catholique.</hi> For his words immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are theſe. <hi>(And yet we ſhall ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre Satan communicate with the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church; while with one minde and mouth we glorifie God,</hi> &amp;c.) Good <hi>Doctor,</hi> deceive not your ſelf, the <hi>Devil</hi> doe's but laugh at you for that idle fancy You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not truly glorifie <hi>God</hi> either in minde or mouth, whileſt you ſeparate your ſelves from Gods Church. Neither can you communica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> whileſt you keep your ſelves out of the communion of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> I told you before <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. that the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> are in ſome ſenſe <hi>Synonymaes,</hi> ſignifying one and the ſame thing. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is that <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church,</hi> out of whoſe communion who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever dyes, ſhall never ſee the face of God.</p>
            <p>Now in what ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is called the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> though I have already ſhewed you, yet I will here
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37695:27"/>
ſomewhat farther explain it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Catholique Church</hi> may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; Firſt, in reſpect of her <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Doctrine;</hi> Secondly, in reſpect of her <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>According to the firſt conſideration, all true particular Churches and Chriſtians, profeſſing and united in one and the ſame <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Communion,</hi> are truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called, the <hi>Catholique Church;</hi> and this is <hi>formally</hi> the <hi>Church Catholique.</hi> We ſay not, that the Roman Church is thus; that is, <hi>formally Catholique:</hi> She is in this ſenſe a part, or member only of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church.</hi> But if we conſider the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church</hi> in reſpect of her Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may truly and properly be called <hi>Catholique;</hi> though not <hi>formally,</hi> yet <hi>cauſally;</hi> becauſe ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> of all other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches of the Chriſtian world, in right of her <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who is St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor, and appointed by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be the ſupream <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Governor</hi> of his whole Church, is the fountain and centre of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> which ſhe infuſes into the whole <hi>Catholique Church;</hi> cauſing all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular members thereof to be united in one and the ſame ſupream earthly <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Governor.</hi> Thoſe then that ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37695:27"/>
to the <hi>Apoſtolique Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and are in communion with the Biſhop thereof, by ſubjecting themſelves to his Authority and Government, acknowledging him <hi>Chriſts Vicar</hi> on earth, &amp; the ſole ſupream <hi>Head</hi> of his Church, may moſt properly be termed, <hi>Roman Catholiques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Province of <hi>Canterbury</hi> conſiſted of many particular Churches, or <hi>Epiſcopal Seas,</hi> all united in the Church or Sea of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> which gave denomination to the whole Province. <hi>Canterbury</hi> it ſelf was not the whole Province; but becauſe it was the <hi>Metropolitan Sea,</hi> the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Mother-Church</hi> of the whole Province, wherein all the particular Seas of that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince</hi> were united, and to whom they yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed obedience; the whole Province received its Denomination from her: which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, being conſidered as a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Dioceſſe,</hi> was but a part or member of the Province of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> So likewiſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> being the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan Sea</hi> of the whole world, the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Mother-Church</hi> of the Chriſtian world, wherein all particular Seas and Churches whatſoever, that are in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the <hi>Church Catholique,</hi> are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; every true Church in particular, may be ſaid to be within the univerſal <hi>Province,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37695:28"/>
or <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> And the <hi>Roman Church</hi> (comprehending under her all particular Churches whatſoever, that are branches and members of the <hi>Catholique,</hi> to whom they all owe obedience and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and in whom they are all united, as in the grand <hi>Metropolitan</hi> Church of the Chriſtian world) may properly be ſtyled the <hi>Catholique Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As then there was the particular Sea, or Church of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> ſo alſo, there is the particular Sea, or Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the univerſal Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And as the particular Sea of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was a part of the Province of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> ſo likewiſe the particular Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is but a part of the univerſal, or <hi>Catholique</hi> Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as truly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending all particular Churches of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world; as the Province of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> contained all the particular Seas of that Province. In brief, as the Sea of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> was to all the particular Seas of that Province; ſo is the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to all the particular Churches of the whole world.</p>
            <p>And by this you may perceive how fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voulous that trivial objection is, which has been ſo often made againſt that expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37695:28"/>
[<hi>Roman Catholique</hi>] as if thoſe words implyed a <hi>contradiction,</hi> in ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Particular,</hi> and yet <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>32. And that the <hi>Roman Church</hi> has e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bin in this ſenſe, the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> viz. as being the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Mother-Church</hi> of all other Chriſtian Churches, appears as plainly as any other point of Faith or Doctrine whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Neither the <hi>Scriptures</hi> themſelves, nor any Doctrine or Article of Faith, written, or unwritten, has deſcended unto us by a more full and ample Tradition, then this D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctrine of the <hi>Primacy</hi> of the <hi>Apostolick Sea</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Supremacy</hi> of the Biſhop thereof over all Churches. So that he that ſhall deny or queſtion this, may as well doubt of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and conſequently of Chriſts coming in the fleſh, and dying for the ſins of the world. Are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the <hi>Ancient Fathers</hi> full of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? has not the univerſal practiſe of the Church in all ages made it ſhine bright, even at this day to the world? Read the <hi>Fathers,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the <hi>Councels,</hi> view the practiſe of Gods Church in all ages, and you will ſoon con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs this to be an apparent and unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable Truth. Beſides, conſider that the <hi>Primacy</hi> and authority of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and his Succeſſors, the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37695:29"/>
it has been a Doctrine univerſally receiv'd, ſo has it no known beginning ſince the time of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the principles of common Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, we ought to imbrace it as an <hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Tradition.</hi> Were not all the churches in the world formerly united and ſubject to the Sea of Rome? Does it not plainly appear in antient Records and Hiſtories, when the Eaſtern churches firſt ſeparated from her communion, and denied obedience to the Biſhop of Rome? Is it not appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent when, and how often thoſe pretended churches have been reconcil'd to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholique Church?</hi> Have not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triatchs of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> themſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and acknowledg'd their obedience and ſubjection to the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> as S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Succeſſor, and <hi>Supreme Head</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Church?</hi> Was there ever any So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of men profeſſing the name of Chriſt, and divided from the Church of Rome, that did not firſt ſeparate themſelves from her communion?</p>
            <p>He then that is no <hi>Roman Catholique,</hi> is none at all, ſince by his Schiſme he has cut himſelf off from the communion of the <hi>Catholique Church,,</hi> and to juſtifie his Schiſme, he muſt neceſſarily fall into Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, by denying this Doctrine of Faith, viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:37695:29"/>
That the <hi>Roman Church</hi> is the Mother and Head of all churches, and the Biſhop there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of appointed by Chriſt, as S. <hi>Peters</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, to be the Supreme Paſtor and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of his Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>I know you will deny this to be a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Faith, but you muſt then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the <hi>Fathers</hi> that taught it, the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels</hi> that declar'd it; The learned <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> (S. <hi>Irenaeus li. 3. c. 3.</hi>) S. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome Epiſt. 57. S. <hi>Cyprian de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitat. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> S. <hi>Baſil concion. de penitent.</hi> S. Leo, Serm. 1. in Natal. Apoſtolor. Petr. &amp; Paul. Gelaſius. in decret. cum 70. Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtin. Epiſt.</hi> 92. as alſo the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Paſtors of the church aſſembled in divers <hi>General Councels:</hi> In the firſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councel of <hi>Nice, Can.</hi> 6. in the Councel of <hi>Epheſus, Act.</hi> 3. in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Calcedon, Act.</hi> 16. and in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, or <hi>relation</hi> ſent to Pope <hi>Leo</hi> from the whole Councel; in the Councel at <hi>Sardis, Can.</hi> 3. could plainly ſee this Doctrine in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and ſo might you too, if you would but open your eyes, and not onely there, but in the Univerſal <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>practiſe</hi> of the church. This Doctrine was receiv'd by the church of <hi>England</hi> for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a 1000. years together, without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; How then come you to be wiſer
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37695:30"/>
then all your Forefathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for ſo many ages? You receiv'd the <hi>Scriptures</hi> from them, and to think that they could no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pret them as well as you, is exceſſive pride, and inſolent madneſs.</p>
            <p>A world of teſtimonies might be brought in confirmation of this Doctrine, but it has been already ſo fully, and ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten prov'd by many learned Catholiques, that it may be altogether unneceſſary for me to add any further proofs, eſpecially ſince my intention is to contain my ſelfe within the bounds of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhort R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ply.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the pretended <hi>Greek Church</hi> (though it abhor and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt your new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, as damnable and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>retical, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears evidently by the book enti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>led <hi>[<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atriarchae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſententia definitiva <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Doctr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a &amp; Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione Wittenberge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſium Theologorum, &amp;c.] An.</hi> 1586.) is now no church at all, as neither are you, but a dead branch lop'd off by Schiſme and H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſie from the Tree of Life, a corrupt member cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> off from Chriſts myſtical body.</p>
            <p>33. But to juſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie this your Schiſm, you alledg certain <hi>Canons</hi> of the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ches, which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e you, that every <hi>Provincial Synod,</hi> is to order all things within the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:37695:30"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If you mean by [<hi>All things</hi>] all things amiſs in matters concerning man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Diſcipline, I can eaſily grant it; but this will not ſatisfie you. <hi>The Church</hi> (you ſay) <hi>did uſually reform, both in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and faith, by Dioceſan, and Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Councels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I confeſs the Pope has confirm'd the Acts and Decr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of divers <hi>Provincial Councels,</hi> even concerning matters of Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, as when they have condemn'd ſome apparent and notorious Hereſie, and ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematiz'd ſuch Heretiques as have oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, either a Doctrine univerſally known, and receiv'd by the whole church, or els ſome Declaration and Definition of a former General Councel: and this is all that you can gather, either out of the <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Code,</hi> or the canons of any Councel, either General o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Provincial.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Code of the Univerſal Church,</hi> by you cited, you muſt know Doctor, that it was compiled by Schiſmatiques and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, who to diminiſh and derogate from the juſt Rights and Prerogatives of the Biſhop of Rome, have apparently fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ied divers canons of the Councel of <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that General Doctrines univerſally receiv'd and taught by the whole Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37695:31"/>
Church, as Doctrines deſcending by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Tradition</hi> from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and declar'd to be ſuch by <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councels;</hi> ſhould be cenſur'd and condemn'd, firſt by one ſingle perſon, and afterwards by thoſe only that followed him in his <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> and Hereſie, for damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able errors muſt neceſſarily appear to any reaſonable and impartial ſpirit, not onely moſt unreaſonable and temerarious, but ſacrilegious and damnable; yet this you have done, charging the whole world with groſs and damnable errors, and alledging Scripture to prove them ſo, to which you appeal to juſtifie your <hi>Apostaſie,</hi> making your ſelves the ſole Judges and <hi>Interpreters</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>34. But I meet with a teſtimony of S. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> of <hi>Poicteurs,</hi> to prove, that <hi>Rome</hi> was once not only diſtinct from, but not ſo much as a part of the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> his words cited are theſe; <hi>Quidam ex vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis firmiſſima fidei conſtantia intra commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionem ſe me am continentes; ſe à coeteris extra Gallias abstinuerunt.</hi> And hence you conclude, that the Church of <hi>France</hi> at that time communicated not with <hi>Rome,</hi> unleſs we can prove <hi>Rome</hi> to be in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is much like your former conſequences: S. <hi>Hilary</hi> was not ſo ſimple
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37695:31"/>
as to think the whole <hi>Catholique Church</hi> was at that time confin'd to one Country or Nation; he only commended the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of his Countrymen, in perſevering in the Catholique Faith, and not commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating with the <hi>Arrians,</hi> which ſwarm'd in divers places out of <hi>France.</hi> If then by thoſe words [<hi>coeteris extra Gallias</hi>] you would exclude all the world, beſides <hi>France,</hi> from the Catholique Church, you will but make your ſelf ridiculous to the world, in making that great Pillar of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church ſpeak that, which all the world knows to be falſe; for at that time, neither the Church of Rome, nor any <hi>Westerne</hi> Church was infected with Arrianiſm, as appears plainly by S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> who was S. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries</hi> Cretanean, and a Biſhop in the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Church, viz. of <hi>Cappado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia;</hi> his word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are theſe, <hi>Vos par erat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligere, quod per Dei gratiam quamplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimi ſint, qui ſidem tuentur Orthodoxam à Patribus Nicaenis ſecundum pic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulam traditam; ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vos per Orientem ſoli ſitis relicti; at verò univerſus quidem Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidens vobiſcum unanimiter &amp; nobiſcum conſpirat. Baſil Epiſt.</hi> 293. Here you ſee the whole Weſtern Church vindicated from that Hereſie, which doubtleſs S. <hi>Hilary</hi> well knew: Thoſe then in <hi>France</hi> that retain'd
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37695:32"/>
their antient Faith, kept themſelves within the communion of the Roman <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> from whoſe communion never yet any ſeparated, but Schiſmatiques and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques</p>
            <p>34. The n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Father</hi> of the Church that I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et with is <hi>Arch-biſhop Lawd</hi> (as you are pleas'd to call him) whoſe authority you have often cited, which I cannot but wond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r at, ſince he was ſo far from being a <hi>Father,</hi> that he neither liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d nor died a <hi>Son</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> but the Doctor, out of that pretended A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch-biſhops book, charges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with four opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pugnant to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in words of <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> viz. 1. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranſubſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ation. 2 Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the bleſſed Sacrament to the Laity in one kind. 3. Invo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of Saints. 4. Adoration of Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though it be not much perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to our preſent purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe to examine theſe D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines according to Scripture; ſince the Doctor conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>twithſtanding her errors, is a tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Church, and a member of the one <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, Sect.</hi> 12. yet becauſe he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lieves the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is juſtly charged with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſound</hi> and <hi>un-Catholike</hi> Doctrines (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is pleaſed to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them) I could not paſs them by; but ſhall endeavour as briefly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37695:32"/>
as may be to vindicate the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from that foul and falſe <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lumnie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>35 Firſt then, <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Roman Catholike</hi> Doctrine) is a true and real change of the total ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Bread and Wine, after, and by vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue of the words of <hi>Conſecration</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc't by the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> into the true, reall, and ſubſtantial Body and Blood of Chriſt. Let us now examine how this Doctrine is repugnant to the plain words of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith, Matth. 26. 26 and Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 14. 22. <hi>This is my Body;</hi> and, <hi>This is my Blood.</hi> The words are plain, and being taken literally, muſt neceſſarily import a change. For that which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> after our <hi>Saviours</hi> conſecration, is (according to the proper and literal ſenſe of the words) the very <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Where is then the <hi>Repugnancy</hi> between this <hi>Doctrine</hi> and the <hi>plain words of Scripture?</hi> Chriſt ſayes of that which was <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine; This is my Body;</hi> and, <hi>This is my Blood.</hi> The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſayes ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo. Inſtead then of a <hi>Repugnancy,</hi> here is a ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> conſent and agreement between the <hi>plain word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of our <hi>Savi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Well, but the words are not to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37695:33"/>
be taken <hi>literally,</hi> but <hi>figuratively.</hi> Be it ſo. Then is this Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> repugnant (at the moſt) but to the <hi>figurative</hi> ſenſe, not to the <hi>plain words,</hi> or <hi>literal</hi> ſenſe of <hi>Scripture.</hi> But to come cloſer; If the Doctor can produce any one Text of <hi>Scripture,</hi> that ſhall be but halfe as plain for the <hi>Metaphorical</hi> or <hi>figurative</hi> ſenſe, or that the Creatures of <hi>'Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> are not really and ſubſtantially changed into the very <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> after <hi>Conſecration,</hi> but retain their former nature and ſubſtance of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> as theſe words of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are for ſuch a change; I' will then (for my part) give the cauſe, and turn <hi>Proteſiant</hi> too, or any thing elſe that Doctor <hi>Boughen</hi> ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me to be. But if he cannot produce any ſuch <hi>Text</hi> (as moſt certainly he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not) then is the Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> and not that of the Church of <hi>Rome, repugnant to the plain words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>36 But to juſtifie your ſelves, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the <hi>Catholike Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtatiation,</hi> you thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret thoſe words; <hi>This is my Body,</hi> &amp;c. viz. <hi>This is a ſigne or figure of my Body:</hi> but what <hi>Scripture</hi> have you for it? What authority? What <hi>Catholique Father,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:37695:33"/>
what <hi>Councel</hi> did ever give that interpeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe words? I confeſs, if there be no true and real change of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> into the ſubſtance of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament,</hi> then will I alſo admit of that interpretation. For if there be no ſuch change, then of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity thoſe creatures of <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> can be but bare ſignes and figures onely of Chriſts <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood.</hi> But behold Gods Providence over his Church. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> fore ſeeing the evaſions and ſhifts that ſome men would uſe to delude the world, and to poiſon the Church with their Heretical Doctrines, in oppoſition to Gods <hi>ſacred Truth,</hi> has in St. <hi>Lukes Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> 22. 19, 20 utterly cut you off even from that very gloſſe and interpretation. The words of the <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the Cup of the new Teſtament in my blood, which</hi> (Cup) <hi>is ſhed for you.</hi> Theſe are the words in the <hi>Original</hi> Language of St. <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel. And though both in the <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> tranſlation the Relative [<hi>which</hi>] may ſeem to refer to [<hi>Blood</hi>] as well as to (<hi>Cup</hi>) yet in the <hi>Greek</hi> it is very plain, that it muſt refer to (<hi>Cup.</hi>) If
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37695:34"/>
then that which was c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ain'd in the cup, was that which was ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d for the ſins of the world, how could it be Wine, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſign or figu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly of <hi>Chriſts</hi> bloud, or any thing elſe, but the true and real bloud of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> For no <hi>ſign</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſigure</hi> of bloud, but Chriſts true and real precious bloud was ſhed for the ſins of the world. I will endeavour to make this Doctrine appear more plaine by this Syllogiſm.</p>
            <p>That which was ſhed for the ſins of the world, was the true and real precious bloud of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which was in the cup was that which was ſhed for the fins of the world. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which was in the cup was the true and real precious bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Major Propoſition</hi> cannot be denied without blaſphemy, the <hi>Minor</hi> is moſt plain by the words of the <hi>Text;</hi> and therefore the <hi>concluſion</hi> muſt neceſſarily follow. Here is no <hi>Fallacy</hi> Doctor, in this <hi>Syllogiſm,</hi> no more terms then ought to be in a <hi>Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm,</hi> but to utterly debar you of your <hi>ſign</hi> or <hi>figure,</hi> I argue thus:</p>
            <p>That which was ſhed for the ſins of the world, was not a ſign or figure only of Chriſts bloud.</p>
            <p>But that which was in the Cup was ſhed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:37695:34"/>
for the ſins of the world. <hi>Ergo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which was in the Cup was not a ſign or figure only of Chriſt's bloud.</p>
            <p>Thoſe words then, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>This is the Cup, the New Teſtament in my Blood,</hi> cannot admit of this interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>This Cup is a ſign of my Blood;</hi> unleſs you will grant that a bare ſign of Chriſt's bloud was ſhed for the ſins of the world, which is high blaſphemy. For it is very plain by the expreſs words of the Text, That the very <hi>Cup</hi> which was the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> in <hi>Chriſt's Blood,</hi> was ſhed for the ſins of the world; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore that <hi>Cup</hi> could not be a ſign onely, but the tru precious bloud of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſay you Doctor? who now main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains Doctrines <hi>repugnant to plain words of Scripture?</hi> you, or the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> you will ſay, perehance, that thoſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly but <hi>Marginal Note,</hi> and are now crept into the <hi>Text,</hi> and that all the <hi>Greek copies</hi> of S. <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel are corrupted. This indeed is the anſwer that one of your great and learned Reformers, <hi>Beza,</hi> has given, though without any ground, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37695:35"/>
proof: but he well knew, that the words of the <hi>Text</hi> were ſo plain, that they could not admit of any other ſhift or evaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and by this ſhift you may evade any authority of <hi>Scripture</hi> that may be brought againſt you; and (had truth no other way to defend it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) we alſo might thus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer any text of <hi>Scripture,</hi> that can be alledged againſt any Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>37. But let us now ſee what the antient Fathers ſay concerning this <hi>fond Doctrine, and repugnant to the plain words of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in the bleſſed Sacrament, has theſe words; <hi>Ecce eum vides, ipſum tangis, ipſum manducas. Et tu quidem veſtimenta cupis videre. Ipſe verò tibi concedit, non tantum videre, verùm &amp; manducare, &amp; tangere, &amp; intrate ſumere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. ad Pop. Antiochen. Behold t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou ſeeſt him</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>thou toucheſt him, thou cateſt him, thou deſireſt to ſee his garments, and he is pleas'd that thou ſhouldeſt not only ſee him, but alſo eat him, touch him, and receive him within thy body.</hi> And that this ſeeing, eating, touching and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Chriſt, is not in a bare figure only<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> appears plainly by theſe words of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37695:35"/>
following in the ſame Homily; <hi>Quod Angeli videntes horreſcunt, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> liberè audent intueri propter emic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntem inde ſplendorem, hoc nos paſcimur. That which the Angels tremble to behold, and ſcarce dare preſume to look upon, by reaſon of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s glorious ſplendor, even this do we feed on.</hi> Mark this good Doctor; Angels tremble not at ſuch mean creatures as <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi> neither have theſe creatures as bare ſigns only of Chriſts body and bloud, ſuch glorious luſtre and ſplendor: Indeed Chriſts true body, which good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques feed on, is a glorious body, ten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>houſand times more glorious then the Sun, though the glory thereof, as being a ſpiritual body, cannot appear to mortal eyes.</p>
            <p>And that you may not fly to your other ſhift, and ſay, that we receive and feed on Chriſts body by Faith and love only, hear what the ſame Father ſayes in the ſame Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, a little before the laſt words cited; <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim illi ſatis fuit hominem fieri, colaphis caedi, &amp; crucifigi, verùm ut ſemet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum nobis commiſcet, &amp; nos fide tantùm, verum &amp; ipſa re, nos ſuum efficit cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus. He</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>was not onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to become man, to be buffeted and crucified, but he alſo incorporates himſelfe into us, and makes us to be
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37695:36"/>
his own body, not by Faith only, but truly and really.</hi> And (<hi>Hom. 61. ad Pop. Antio.</hi>) the ſame Father thus ſaith; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num corpus e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>icimur &amp;c. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non tantùm per charitatem hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iamus, verum etiam ipſa re, in illam miſceamur carnem; hoc nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> per eſcam efficitur quam largitus est nobis. We are become one and the ſame body</hi> [with Chriſt, viz by the power of the bleſſed Sacrament] <hi>That then we may be ſo not by charity only, but truly and really let us be incorporated into that fleſh, for this is brought to paſs by that food which he has given us.</hi> And now Doctor, how is it poſſible that Bread and Wine ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporare us into <hi>Chriſt's</hi> fleſh; or that bare figures ſhould make us become one body with him, and that not only ſpiritually and myſtically, but truly and really? But let us hear the ſame Father ſpeak once more; (<hi>Hom. 60. ad Pop. Antioch.) Nos Miniſtrorum tenemus locum, qui verò ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a &amp; immuta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ipſe eſt. We ſupply the place of Miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, but he that ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies and changes them is</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>himſelf.</hi> Here is a change, and that by the power of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt, not the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the Faith of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icant.</p>
            <p>38. Let us now hear what S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:37695:36"/>
ſayes, (<hi>de Sacram. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. 4. c. 4.) Panis iſte panis eſt ante verba Sacramentorum; ubi acceſſerit conſecratio, de pane fit caro Chriſti; quomodo poteſt qui panis eſt corpus eſſe Chriſti? Conſecratione. Before the words of Conſecration it is bread; as ſoon as Conſecration comes, of bread, it is made the fleſh of Chriſt.</hi> (Mark thoſe words. <hi>De pane, of, or from bread) How can that which is bread, become the Body of Christ? by conſecration.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Si ergo tanta vis eſt in ſermone Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Jeſu, ut inciperent eſſe quae non erant, quanto magis operatorius eſt, ut quae erant, in aliud commutentur? If then there be ſo great po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er in the word of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that thoſe things which had no being, ſhould begin to have a being; how much rather does it effect, that thoſe things which had a being, ſhould be chang'd into an other ſubstance?</hi> Here then is a change, a ſubſtantial or eſſential change, as appears plainly by thoſe words (<hi>in aliud commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentur</hi>) (And what does a ſubſtantial or an eſſential change differ from Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation?) and this change is wrought principally by Chriſts omnipotent power, inſtrumentally by the words of Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion pronounc't by the <hi>Prieſt;</hi> then doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, not by the faith and charity of the communicant.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:37695:37"/>39. Some of your Sect I know have been very forward to acknowledg <hi>Chriſt</hi> truly and really preſent in the <hi>bleſſed Sacrament;</hi> nay, that Chriſts body is really preſent there, but how? by faith; but what you mean by that expreſſion, [<hi>by Faith</hi>] I know not; howbelt I am ſure you muſt underſtand either the manner, or the means of Chriſts body being really preſent there: If by thoſe words you underſtand the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Chriſts body being preſent in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, then is his body preſent there <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſively</hi> only; for by Faith the ſoul ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends Chriſts body, which in that appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion is ſpiritually preſent to the faithful. and worthy communicant: but how then can this be clear'd from a contradiction? for to be preſent <hi>apprehenſively</hi> only by <hi>faith,</hi> is contradiſtinguiſht from being truly and really preſent; ſo that to ſay, Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is truly and really in the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by <hi>faith,</hi> is in effect to ſay, Chriſts body is truly and really in the Sacrament, and, Chriſts body is not truly and really in the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>And if by <hi>Faith</hi> you underſtand the means, that is, either the <hi>meritorious</hi> (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that word) or <hi>inſtrumental</hi> cauſe of Chriſts body being really p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſent in the Sacrament, or a neceſſary condition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37695:37"/>
which Chriſt's body cannot be really preſent there: then firſt you contradict the forecited Fathers, who ſay, that Chriſt's body is really preſent in the Sacrament by the omnipotent power of Chriſt in the words of <hi>Conſecration</hi> pronounc't by the <hi>Prieſt.</hi> Secondly, this <hi>real preſence</hi> of Chriſt's body, muſt be either by a change of one ſubſtance into another, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently by that which the <hi>Church</hi> calls <hi>Tranſubstantiation;</hi> (and then you will not accuſe that Doctrine for being <hi>repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the plain words of Scripture</hi>) or elſe by conſubſtantiation; and then why do you not adore it? and why do you charge the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> with Idolatry for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oring Chriſt whereſover he is <hi>corporally</hi> preſent, ſince his <hi>Humanity</hi> is inſeparably and <hi>Hypoſtatically</hi> united to his <hi>Divinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>40. Let us now hear what <hi>Euſebius E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſenus</hi> ſayes, <hi>Inviſibilis ſacerdos viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biles creaturas in ſubſtantiam corporis &amp; ſanguinis ſui, verbo ſuo ſecretâ poteſtate convertit:</hi> Theſe words are cited out of the <hi>Author</hi> by <hi>Gratian. (de conſecrat. diſt. 2. c. quia corpus.) The inviſible Priest</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>converts the viſible creatures into the ſubstance of his body and bloud by his word, by his ſecret power.</hi> How can <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation</hi> be more plainly exprſs't, then in theſe words? Or what is <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation,</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:37695:38"/>
but a change of creatures into another ſubſtance? Many more teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies might be brought both from the antient and modern <hi>Fathers</hi> in confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Doctrine, which to avoid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity I have omitted.</p>
            <p>41. This Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> being proved (as it hath been both by <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi>) is a ſufficient ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification of the <hi>adminiſtration of the bleſſed Sacrament to the Laity in one kind,</hi> (the bleſſed Sacrament being integrally as well as eſſentially contain'd under either kind) which is the ſecond Doctrine repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (as you ſay) to the plain words of <hi>Scripture.</hi> But where is it ſaid in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>You ſhall not adminiſter the bleſſed Sacrament to the Laity in one kind onely?</hi> Or where is it ſaid; <hi>You ſhall administer the bleſſed Sacrament to the Laity under both kinds?</hi> If any ſuch precept be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in plain words of <hi>Scripture,</hi> why has it never yet been diſcovered? and if there be no ſuch plain precept there, then the adminiſtration of the bleſſed <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the Laity in one kind, cannot be <hi>repugnant to plain words of Scripture;</hi> the unlawfulneſs thereof c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but (at the moſt) deducible from ſome places of the Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which being obſcur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37695:38"/>
cannot be better interpreted then by the antient and univerſal practiſe of the church, which in former ages eſteemed the adminiſtration of the bleſſed Sacrament to the Laity, under one or both kinds, a thing indifferent, and upon ſeveral occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons practiſed both; as when the <hi>Mani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hees</hi> abſtaining from wine, as a thing unlawful, condemned the uſe of the <hi>Chalice</hi> in the bleſſed Sacrament, divers <hi>Catholique Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> in oppoſition to thoſe Herctiques, commended the practiſe of communicating under both kinds: and afterwards, when this errour was exploded, and a contrary ſucceeded, viz. an opinion of certain He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, who maintain'd the neceſſity of communicating under both kinds, becauſe (as they ſaid) Chriſt was not wholly and entirely comtain'd under either: Then the church to prevent a farther Schiſm, declared the lawfulneſs and ſufficiency of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating in one kind only, and did withall forbid the adminiſtration of the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament under both. The indifferency of communicating in one or both kinds, and the antien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> practiſe of the church in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therunto, I have elſ where ſhown, Sect. 20 wherefore here I will only add thoſe words of our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> in confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mation thereof, Jo. 6. 59. <hi>He that eateth this
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37695:39"/>
bread ſhall live for ever.</hi> If then the end of the inſtitution of the bleſſed Sacrament, which is <hi>eternal life,</hi> may be obtain'd by eating only the body of Chriſt; it cannot be neceſſary for ſalvation to communicate in both kinds, ſince ſalvation may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by communicating under the <hi>Species</hi> of Bread only; and theſe words are a plain expoſition of thoſe words precedent, ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten alledg'd againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by Heretiques, Jo. 6. 54. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs ye ſhall eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his bloud, ye ſhall not have life in you:</hi> whereby it appeares that the conjunctive [<hi>And</hi>] is to be taken disjunctively for [<hi>Or</hi>] as it is in thoſe words of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> Act. 3. 6. <hi>Silver and gold have I none;</hi> where the ſenſe is, <hi>Silver or gold have I none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, Chriſts body and bloud being entirely contain'd under either <hi>Species,</hi> whoſoever receives his body, muſt alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his bloud: and ſince <hi>Bloud</hi> is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſubject of drinking, not of eating, he that any way receives Chriſts bloud, may be ſaid to drink it, drinking being as properly refer'd to the <hi>ſubject,</hi> as to the <hi>action:</hi> Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fore though that word [<hi>And</hi>] were to be taken conjunctively (as it is not) yet were it ſufficient to communicate under one <hi>Species</hi> only; becauſe whoſoever
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37695:39"/>
eats Chriſts body, muſt alſo neceſſarily drink his bloud.</p>
            <p>Thoſe other Texts ſo much urged by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> Mat. 26. 27. <hi>Drink ye all of this:</hi> And <hi>Luc. 22. 19. Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me,</hi> are very impertinent; thoſe words being ſpoken to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> only, and to them as <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> not in relation to the <hi>Sacrament</hi> only, but to the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and their Succeſſors, the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> were to offer up for a continual commemoration of <hi>Chriſts Paſſion.</hi> Beſides, it is to be obſerv'd, that ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> uſed not thoſe words abſolutely, [<hi>Do this in remembrance of me</hi>] but only when he gave his <hi>Body</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Species of <hi>Bread;</hi> and when he adminiſtred the <hi>Cup,</hi> then he uſed them conditionally; Do this, as often as ye ſhall drink, in remembrance of me.</p>
            <p>42. The third <hi>fond Doctrine, and repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the plain words of Scripture,</hi> is, <hi>invocation of Saints.</hi> But where are thoſe plain words of Scripture? I have read the Old and New <hi>Teſtament,</hi> yet never could find any ſuch precept as this, <hi>Thou ſhalt not,</hi> or, <hi>no man ſhall invocate Saints.</hi> Or, <hi>Thou ſhalt not deſire the Saints to offer up thy prayers to God.</hi> Or, <hi>Thou ſhalt not pray to the Saints to pray for thee;</hi> and if no
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37695:40"/>
ſuch precept can be found in Scripture, in plain terms (as never any ſuch was yet diſcovered there) then doubtleſs this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is not <hi>repugnant to the plain words of Scripture.</hi> But on the contrary, I find this Doctrine, viz. <hi>That the bleſſed Saints may be invocated,</hi> very probably (if not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily) deducible from <hi>Scripture.</hi> For if <hi>Angels</hi> may be invocated, why may not <hi>Saints,</hi> who ſee God as well as the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> and are in the ſame ſtate of bliſs and glory with thoſe bleſſed Spirits? but that the <hi>Angels</hi> may be invocated, is moſt plain in divers places of Scripture. As from the examples of <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18. who in that one chapter prayed ſix times to the <hi>Angel: Of Lot, Gen. 19. Of Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 48. 15. where <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſſing the ſons of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> after he had invocated his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel Guardian,</hi> uſeth theſe words, <hi>And let my name, and the name of my Fathers,</hi> Abraham <hi>and</hi> Iſaac <hi>be invocated on them.</hi> Which words are far more plain for <hi>Inv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints,</hi> then any place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that you or any other can alledg, can make againſt it.</p>
            <p>And I deſire you to take S. <hi>Auguſtives</hi> obſervation along with you upon thoſe words, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde notandum est</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolùm ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itionem, ſed &amp; invocationem
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37695:40"/>
dici aliquando, quae non Dei, ſed hominum ſunt. Aug. in Gen. to. 3. Whence we may obſerve, that ſometimes, not only hearing, but invocation alſo is ſpoken of, as not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to God</hi> (only) <hi>but to men.</hi> So likewiſe from the example of <hi>Moſes, (Ex. 32.)</hi> where the <hi>Angel</hi> of God appeared to him in a flaming buſh, S. <hi>Stephen</hi> himſelf interpreting it ſo, <hi>Act.</hi> 7 30. Of <hi>Gedeon, Iudg.</hi> 11. 6. Of <hi>Ioſuah, Ioſ.</hi> 5. 15. who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate adored an <hi>Angel,</hi> knowing him to be an <hi>Angel.</hi> Of S. <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 19. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. which places ſome of you have moſt ridiculouſly alledged againſt this Doctrine of <hi>Invocation of Saints and Angels.</hi> For that bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> either knew him to be an <hi>Angel,</hi> or not; if he knew him not to be an <hi>Angel,</hi> then he miſtook the <hi>Angel</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as probably he might, becauſe the Angel ſpake in the perſon of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaying; <hi>I am Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha and Omega, &amp;c.</hi> and then the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> might offer to adore him with divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which the <hi>Angel</hi> diſcovering himſelf to be but an <hi>Angel,</hi> might juſtly reprove: and this interpretation S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives of it, <hi>q. 61. in Gen.</hi> Or elſe S. <hi>John</hi> knew him to be but an <hi>Angel,</hi> and if ſo, then it cannot be reaſonably ſuppos'd, that the bleſſed <hi>Apostle</hi> could ſin in worſhipping the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37695:41"/>
               <hi>Angel;</hi> becauſe he having receiv'd the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as well as the reſt of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> and being ſo dear to our bleſſed <hi>Saviour,</hi> inſomuch that he is ſtiled beyond all the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles, The beloved Diſciple, Jo.</hi> 16. 23. could not but know, even as the <hi>Angel</hi> himſelf, what worſhip was due to God, and what to an <hi>Angel.</hi> Beſides, if S. <hi>Iohn's</hi> adoration of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> had been reprov'd by the <hi>Angel,</hi> as in it ſelf ſimply unlawful; can it be imagined that ſo great an <hi>Apostle,</hi> ſo great a Prophet and Evangeliſt, would a ſecond time fall into the ſame error? If then upon a miſtake the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> adored the Angel for God, thoſe words of the <hi>Angel</hi> may be a prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, or rebuke, otherwiſe it was but a modeſt refuſal of the <hi>Angel,</hi> who ſeeing how dear S. <hi>Iohn</hi> was to Chriſt, and what ſecret and ſublime myſteries had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd unto him, more then to any of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> plainly foreſaw that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhould one day be exalted to an higher degree of glory in heaven, and ſhould be neerer to God then the <hi>Angel</hi> himſelf; ſo that, in brief, beſides the lawfulneſs of adoring <hi>Angels</hi> (and conſequently Saints) there is nothing elſe from this place ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveable, but S. <hi>Iohn's</hi> humility in ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Angel,</hi> and the <hi>Angels</hi> modeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in refuſing the adoration.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:37695:41"/>If then <hi>Abraham, Lot, Iacob, Ioſuah, Gedeon,</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> that great <hi>Apostle,</hi> and beloved Diſciple, might lawfully adore and invocate <hi>Angels,</hi> why may not we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate the bleſſed Saints, who together with the <hi>Angels,</hi> ſee and praiſe God continually? why may not we deſire the aſſiſtance of their prayers to God for us?</p>
            <p>43. But perchance this <hi>Invocation of Saints</hi> is ſome new upſtare Doctrine, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly invented, and brought in by the Church of <hi>Rome. Anſw.</hi> As new as it is, if either you, Doctor, or any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> in the world, can ſhew but as much <hi>Antiquity</hi> for your <hi>Religion,</hi> as I can for this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, I will then ſhake hands with you, and become a Proteſtant my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Let us then look back towards the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, and examine the antient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and practiſe of the Church. <hi>Theode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> who lived <hi>An. Chriſti</hi> 430. proves this Doctrine by the general practiſe of the Church in his time; <hi>Qui in peregrinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem aliquam mittuntur</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>petunt instanter hos (ſanctos Martyres) ſieri viae comites, &amp; duces itineris; qui redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum nanciſcuntur afferunt confeſſionem gratiae, non ut Deos ipſos ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>untes, ſed ut homines divinos orantes, &amp; interceſſores pro ipſis fieri poſtulantes, Serm. 8. de cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand. Graecor. affectionib. (ſive) de Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyribus.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37695:42"/>
Thoſe that undertake any journey earneſtly, deſire them</hi> (the holy Martyrs) <hi>to accompany and guide them in their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and thoſe that return in ſafety, offer up an acknowledgment of their favours, making their addreſſes unto them, not as Gods, but praying unto them as Divine men, and beſeeching them to become inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us hear <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Councel of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> held <hi>An.</hi> 431. where himſelf was Pope <hi>Cel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtines</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legate; <hi>Salve à nobis D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ipara Maria, per quam preti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa Cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bratur, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doratur univerſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rbe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ail, O Mary, Mother of God, by whom the precious Croſs is reverenc't, and ador'd through ut the whole world.</hi> Let us hear S. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (Epiſt, 205. ad Iulian Apoſt.</hi>) who lived in the yeare of Chriſt 370. <hi>Sanctos Apoſtolos Prophetas, &amp; Martyres i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, ut apud Deum ſuppli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, &amp; characteres imaginum ipſorum honoro &amp; veneror his traditis à ſanctis Apoſtolis. I invocate the holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>poſtles, Prophets, and Martyrs, that they may pray to God</hi> (for us) <hi>I honor and reverence their Images; theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delivered unto us by the holy Apoſtles.</hi> Here we find that almoſt 1300. years ſince, this Doctrine of <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:37695:42"/>
honouring their Images, was receiv'd by the Church as an <hi>Apostolical Tradition:</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf (<hi>Inſtit. li. 3. c. 20. n. 22.</hi> ſpeaking of the third Councel of <hi>Carthage,</hi> whereat S, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, acknowledges, that at that time <hi>Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints</hi> was practis'd by the Church. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tempestate</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>moris e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat dicere; ſancta Maria, aut, ſancte Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, or a pro nobis. At that time it was a cuſtome to ſay, Saint Mary, or Saint Peter, pray for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Hierom (Tom. 1. pa. 59. edit. Pariſ.</hi> and <hi>To. p. 122. edit. Baſilienſ.</hi>) and S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe li. de viduis,</hi> deduce and prove this Doctrine out of Scripture; and certainly theſe holy and reverend <hi>Fathers</hi> could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret Scripture as well as <hi>Iohn Calvin.</hi> Neither is it imagineable, that either theſe Fathers, or <hi>Theodoret,</hi> or S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> would maintain a Doctrine, and that by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which ſhould be <hi>repugnant to plain words of Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, that Doctrine which has been confirm'd by the atteſtation of <hi>Divine Miracles</hi> muſt be true; but this Doctrine of <hi>Invocation of Saints</hi> has been thus atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, therefore it muſt be true. The <hi>major</hi> is proved out of <hi>Scripture, Mar.</hi> 6. 20. and cannot be denied or queſtion'd without
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37695:43"/>
blaſphemy: and if you deny the <hi>minor,</hi> you muſt give <hi>Theodoret</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the lye, the former proving it in the forecited place, (<hi>li. 8. de Martyrib.</hi>) the later (<hi>De civitat. Dei li. 22. c.</hi> 8.) where he recounts above a hundred Miracles (of ſome whereof he was an eye-witneſs) wrought by God, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the prayers at the <hi>Monument</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques</hi> of S. <hi>Stephen;</hi> and that prayers were made to the Saints, who alſo heard and underſtood the prayers of ſuch as prayed unto them, and the manner how they underſtand our prayers, and that they grant ſavours to thoſe that pray unto them, S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> will tell you plainly in his 15. and 16. <hi>chap. de cur. pro. mort. ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is <hi>Invocarion of Scints</hi> vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, both from <hi>repugnancy to Scripture,</hi> and <hi>novelty.</hi> I come now to the fourth and laſt <hi>fond Doctrine,</hi> wherewith the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtands charg'd; which is, <hi>Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>44. For the better clearing the Church from this charge, I thought it neceſſary to declare the Doctrine of the Catholique Church concerning Images, which is this, <hi>The Images of Christ, of the Mother of God, and other Saints, may be had and kept, and due honour and reverence is to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37695:43"/>
be given unto them;</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appeares by the <hi>Profeſſion of Faith</hi> compos'd and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riz'd by the Councel of <hi>Trent.</hi> Where are the plain words of <hi>Scripture</hi> to which this Doctriue is repugnant? Where is it ſaid in Scripture; in plain and expreſs words, <hi>Thou ſhalt not give any worſhip, honor, or reuerence to the Images of Chriſt, or of his Mother, or of other Saints?</hi> The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in divers places forbids <hi>Divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> to be given to <hi>Idols,</hi> or <hi>falſe Gods,</hi> as <hi>Exod. 20. Levit. 26. Deut. 5. Iſay</hi> 40. &amp;c. but where is it ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not worſhip, honor, or reverence the holy Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Christ, or of his Saints?</hi> Thoſe Texes of Scripture forbid only, that the worſhip due to God, ſhould be given to creatures, Idols, or falſe Gods; where then is the repugnancy between the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and plain words of <hi>Scripture?</hi> The Scripture for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids <hi>Idolatry,</hi> ſo does, and ever did the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Scripture forbids Divine worſhip to be given to any thing but God, ſo does the Church of Rome. God forbids <hi>Graven Images,</hi> that is <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols,</hi> to be ſet up and adored with Divine worſhip; and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands due honor and reverence to be given to holy Images of Chriſt, and his Saints.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37695:44"/>
I muſt again demand, where is the repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy between this Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the plain words of Scripture? If you ſay, that thoſe words <hi>Ex 20. Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not fall downe and worſhip it,</hi> are plain againſt this Doctrine, I will confeſs, that they are as plain againſt it, as any words of <hi>Scripture,</hi> either of the Old or New <hi>Teſtament;</hi> but if you argue from theſe words, (as many of your Sect have done) that therefore it is not lawfull to honor or reverence the holy Images of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Saints; here is then a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>fallacy, A dicto ſecundum quod, ad di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ſimpliciter.</hi> For neither are all <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> but only <hi>Idols,</hi> nor all <hi>worſhip,</hi> but only <hi>Divine worſhip</hi> forbidden in thoſe words. I may as well conclude, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſaid in Scripture, God only is to be worſhipt, therefore we muſt not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Kings, Princes, and Magiſtrates. But good Doctor, as there is a <hi>Divine worſhip</hi> due to God, and to him only, ſo there is a <hi>civil worſhip</hi> due to Kings, Princes, and Magiſtrates; and another ſort of worſhip due to <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints:</hi> and ſo likewiſe there is a reverence and honor due to the holy Images of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> not a divine, or abſolute, but a certain far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37695:44"/>
worſhip, and meerly relative. Is it a greater ſin in me to adore <hi>Chriſt</hi> in or before his <hi>image,</hi> then it was in <hi>Iacob</hi> to adore <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his <hi>Rod</hi> or Sccpter? S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 21.) that <hi>Iacob</hi> adored the top of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Rod: wherein ſaith S. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſost. Hom.</hi> 66. and <hi>Theodoret q.</hi> 108. in <hi>Gen. Ioſephs</hi> dream was fulfilled, viz. That his Father ſhould worſhip him. From <hi>Iacob</hi> under the <hi>Old,</hi> let us come to the Fathers under the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> You have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready heard S. <hi>Baſil Epist. ad Iulian,</hi> 205. publikely profeſſing, that he adored the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the holy <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Martyrs;</hi> and that this kind of <hi>Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Images,</hi> was an <hi>Apostolical Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> You have heard what S. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>A. lexandria</hi> delivered in his Homily before the Councel of <hi>Epheſus</hi> (the third General Councel) where himſelf was <hi>Preſident</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pope <hi>Celeſtine;</hi> it will not be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to repeat his words, <hi>Hail</hi> Mary, <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God, by whom the precious Croſs is reverenc't and adored throughout the whole world.</hi> Here is the Image of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Croſs</hi> adored throughout the whole world (according to S <hi>Cyril</hi>) in relation to him that died on it: and it is more then probable, that the whole Church then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in that Councel, did practiſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37695:45"/>
that <hi>Adoration;</hi> otherwiſe, doubtleſs, the Councel would have declar'd their diſſent from S. <hi>Cyril,</hi> and their diſlike of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. And now can any reaſonable man imagine, that thoſe holy and learned <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> S. <hi>Baſil,</hi> S. <hi>Cyril,</hi> and S. <hi>Chryſostome, Theodoret,</hi> ſhould maintain, and the whole Councel of <hi>Epheſus</hi> approve of a Doctrine, or practiſe <hi>repugnant to plain words of Scripture?</hi> Beſides, it is not as lawful to adore the <hi>Images,</hi> as the <hi>Reliques</hi> of <hi>Saints?</hi> and is it not known to all the world with what holy zeale and bitterneſs S. <hi>Hierome</hi> inveigh's againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilantius,</hi> for oppoſing and condemning that practiſe? Does he not charge <hi>Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius</hi> with <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> for ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Adoration</hi> of ſacred Reliques? Has not God by many apparent <hi>Miracles</hi> approv'd this holy practiſe? (<hi>Auguſt. de Civit. Dei lib. 22. c.</hi> 8.)</p>
            <p>Tho teſtimonies that might be brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o confirm this Doctrine, would ſwell to a large volume. I will only add this, that in the time of the ſecond General Councel, it was a cuſtome to adorn Churches with Images; as appears by S. <hi>Gregory Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nzen, (Epiſt. 49. ad Olympium)</hi> who ſate in that Councel: as alſo by this teſtimony out of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> who ſate in the firſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> held about the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37695:45"/>
year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 325. that in his time, and long before, Images of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were made and adored, <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ. li. 7. c.</hi> 14. his words are theſe; <hi>Et nos A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum ipſius</hi> (Chriſti) <hi>imagines,</hi> Pauli, <hi>&amp;</hi> Petri, <hi>&amp; ipſius etiam Chriſti vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus per colores in picturis conſervat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, antiquis, ut par eſt, immutabiliter ſolitis hoc modo honorare, &amp;c. We alſo have ſeen the Images of Christs Apoſtles,</hi> Paul, <hi>and</hi> Peter, <hi>as alſo of Chriſt himſelf, preſerv'd in Pictures by colours, our Anceſtors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wont, as it is fit, to honor them after this manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I paſs by the authority of S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> who very learnedly and copiouſly defends this Doctrine (<hi>li. 9. Epiſt.</hi> 9.) of <hi>Leonti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> S. <hi>Gregories</hi> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tanean, Biſhop of <hi>Neapolis</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> who purpoſely wrote in defence of this Doctrine: As alſo of the ſecond General Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> which defin'd and declar'd this Doctrine to be an <hi>Apoſtolical Tradition,</hi> condemning and anathematizing the <hi>Iconoclaſts,</hi> or Image<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakers, as Heretiques. I omit alſo the preſent practiſe of the pretended <hi>Greek Church,</hi> which you may plainly read in <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>remias,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Constantinople; (Cerſura Orient. Eccleſ. c.</hi> 21.) where he maintains and vindicates this Doctrine of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:37695:46"/>
honoring and reverencing Images from ſuperſtition and Idolatry, againſt the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi> All theſe I purpoſely paſs by, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I will contain my ſelf within the firſt five hundred years, to which you have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed. You ſee then, <hi>Doctor,</hi> the practiſe and doctrine of the Church within five hundred years after <hi>Christs birth,</hi> in the Fathers and Councels above-cited. Be now as good as your word, ſubmit to their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for trial of the truth of <hi>Religion,</hi> and you will (by Gods grace) ſoon return to your Mother, the <hi>Roman Catholique Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is that charge, which you ſay (<hi>Sect.</hi> 28. of your ſecond anſwer) <hi>We know not how to ſhift off,</hi> fully anſwer'd.</p>
            <p>45. In the next <hi>Sect.</hi> 25. I meet with ſome Authorities againſt the Juriſdiction of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> The firſt is of S. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus,</hi> who <hi>ſharply checked and reproved Biſhop</hi> Victor <hi>for keeping ſuch a ſtir about the obſervation of Eaſter, and excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating divers Churches, becauſe they would not ſtoop to his lure. Anſw.</hi> That Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> who govern'd the Church about 200. years after the birth of our Saviour, excommunicated the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> for their too much Judaizing in the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Eaſter, is a very ſtrong argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:37695:46"/>
you. For firſt, S. <hi>Victor</hi> was a pious and bleſſed man, and therefore it cannot be reaſonably imagin'd, that he would u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp a power which <hi>Chriſt</hi> never gave him. Secondly, thoſe Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> never proteſted againſt his Juriſdiction over them, which certainly they would have done, had not the Church in thoſe dayes eſteemed the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> the common <hi>Paſtor</hi> of Chriſts Church, and appointed by Chriſt to be under him, the ſupreme <hi>Head</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Thirdly, when S. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> expoſtulated with him for his ſeverity in excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Eaſtern Churches,</hi> he never char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him for tranſgreſſing the bounds of his Juriſdiction, or for uſurping a power which Chriſt never delegated unto him, which in all probability he would have done, had he not look't on the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the ſupreme viſible Head of Chriſts Church. But becauſe he conceiv'd not their offence ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainous, as to deſerve ſo heavy a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; he therefore took upon him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> by way of friendly and fraternal correction, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſomtimes did S. <hi>Peter;</hi> and as S. <hi>Paul</hi> never queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd S. <hi>Peters</hi> Juriſdiction, nor denied him to be the chief and Head of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;</hi> ſo neither did S. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> nor any of the Eaſtern Church, that were excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37695:47"/>
by Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> queſtion or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt the Juriſdiction of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thoſe words of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in the Councel of <hi>Carthage,</hi> are to be underſtood of the <hi>African</hi> Biſhops only, who being of equal authority, could not excommunicate one another: They exclude not the <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> otherwiſe S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> had contradicted himſelf, who ſayes plainly (<hi>Epiſt. ad Quintinum,</hi> and <hi>Serm. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on. patient.</hi>) that Chriſt built his Church upon S. <hi>Peter:</hi> and (<hi>li. 4. ep. 8. ad Cornel.</hi>) that the Unity of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church conſiſts in the communion with the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi> His words you ſhall find hereafter. <hi>Sect.</hi> 58.</p>
            <p>In the next place <hi>Sect.</hi> 26. enters an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Cappado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia, Firmilianus,</hi> ſpeaking thus to Pope <hi>Stephen: Teipſum excidiſti, noli te fallere, Miſtake no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy ſelf, thou Biſhop of Rome, while thou go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st about to caſt out others, by this preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thou haſt caſt off thy ſelf from the body of Chriſt, which is his Church. Anſ.</hi> By your leave, <hi>Doctor,</hi> you miſunderſtand <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milianus,</hi> he ſpeaks not as you would have him. Indeed he was very angry with Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> becauſe he excommunicated him for maintaining that Heretical Doctrine of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37695:47"/>
rebaptizing Heretiques: He never told Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> that he had cut himſelfe off from the Church, becauſe he excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated <hi>Firmilianus,</hi> or any other <hi>Biſhop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but he was willing the world ſhould think that Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> in defending the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Heretiques to be lawful, had ſided with them in their Hereſies, and had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cut himſelf off from the Church, not becauſe he had excommunicated any Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <hi>Biſhop</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> but becauſe (as <hi>Firmilianus</hi> conceiv'd) he too much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with Heretiques. And you know, Doctor, the very ſame Doctrine, for which <hi>Firmilianus</hi> was excommunicated, was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, in the firſt General Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> declar'd to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heretical.</p>
            <p>46. <hi>It is common</hi> (ſay you) <hi>in theſe daies, even with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe that conſcientiouſly pretend to truth, not to be content with the Rule of Faith, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as once delivered to the Saints, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from them by the Primitive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> tranſmitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o poſterity; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> after n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w invention<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſe courſes I abhor with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctor, you have directly given ſentence againſt your ſelf: If you will but examine the Doctrines of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and your Doctrines, wherein you
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:37695:48"/>
oppoſe and differ from her: but according to S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Rule (<hi>de Baptiſ. li. 2. c.</hi> 23.) and the principles of common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, you will ſoon diſcover which is the Rule of Faith deliver'd to the <hi>Saints,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from them by the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> &amp; ſo tranſmitted to poſterity; and which are thoſe <hi>new inventions:</hi> For it is impoſſible, that either you, or any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> in the world can ſhew or prove, that any one Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which the <hi>Roman Church</hi> at this day maintains and teaches, had its beginning, or crept into the Church ſince Chriſt and his Apoſtles: Whereas on the contrary, there is not one Doctrine wherein you dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> but may be, and has been often already prov'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to have begun ſince the time of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> How then do you abhor with a perfect hatred theſe courſes, ſince you have imbrac't new <hi>inventions,</hi> and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally forſaken the <hi>Rule of Faith delivered to the Saints, receiv'd from them by the Primitive Church, and tranſmitted to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity?</hi> If it can be clearly demonſtrated, that all your Doctrines wherein you differ from the <hi>Roman Church</hi> are new; and if it cannot be proved, that any one Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> had its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſince the Apoſtles, either you abhor
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:37695:48"/>
not theſe courſes with a perfect hatred (as you profeſs) or elſe you muſt in all points imbrace the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>47. But ſtay; Here I meet with a brace of fierce Syllogiſmes, that fly furiouſly at the very throat of the poor Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The firſt is this.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>That Church which hath erred, is not the Pillar and ground of truth. But</item>
                  <item>The Church of Rome hath erred.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo: The Church of Rome is not the Pillar and ground of Truth.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
The <hi>minor</hi> is thus prov'd by the ſecond Syllogiſm.
<list>
                  <item>That Church which hath profeſſed Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſm, Arrianiſm, Eutychianiſm, hath erred: But,</item>
                  <item>The Church of Rome hath profeſſed all theſe:</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Church of Rome hath erred.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>minor</hi> (you ſay) you have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently proved <hi>Sect.</hi> 18. 27. But I have more ſufficiently proved, that you have there proved nothing at all, but are forc't to fly to moſt ridiculous ſhifts and fallacies; and thoſe fallacies I meet with here again, <hi>Sect.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. where the Church of Rome is charg'd with <hi>all ſins almoſt imagineable,</hi> and divers Authors are cited to prove that charge. Let us ſee then how they prove it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:37695:49"/>
               <hi>Plarina</hi> and <hi>Onuphrius</hi> are produc't to prove, that <hi>Schiſm was rais'd there.</hi> What then? Was the Church of Rome therefore Schiſmatical, becauſe ſome rais'd a Schiſm there? I told you before, that the Authors only of the Schiſm, and thoſe that adhere to them are the Schiſmatiques, they have forſaken the Church, they have cut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves off from Chriſts body; the Church it ſelf remains ſtill ſound and entire. But that <hi>Stella</hi> and <hi>Almain</hi> ſhould charge the Church of Rome with Hereſie, to ſay no more, is moſt falſe. I muſt once more put you in mind what <hi>Stella</hi> ſayes in the place by you cited, Luc. 22. 31. <hi>Eccleſia Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochena, Alexandrina, &amp; Conſtantinopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana ſaepe defecerunt à fide, Eccleſia verò Romana nunquam defecit. The Church of Antioch, Alexandria, and Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have often fallen from the Faith, but the Church of Rome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fell from the Faith.</hi> Remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and never produce <hi>Stella</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> purpoſe. And what if there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd great ſinners in the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> what is this to her Faith and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> What if She wanted Reformation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Diſcipline? what is that to Her belief? What if ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me Popes have been vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious? was the Church of Rome there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37695:49"/>
vicious? and what if ſome Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> had fallen from their Faith, muſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> therefore forſake her Faith?</p>
            <p>There was a time (you ſay, out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius, An. Chriſti 908. n.</hi> 5. and <hi>An. 931. n.</hi> 1.) <hi>when</hi> Marozia, <hi>and her Daughter (a couple of lewd Strumpets) diſpoſed of the Popedome for many years, ſo that none poſſeſſed that Chair, but Boys, Fools, and Kuaves Anſw.</hi> I pray, tell me, Doctor, did the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at that time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt only of Boys, Fools, and Knaves? When the Popes were Boys, wasthere not one man, woman, or child in the whole Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Or when they were Fools, or Knaves, were there then no wiſe or honeſt men in that Church? Theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences muſt follow as well as the other. For if it follow, that becauſe ſome Popes have been vicious, therefore the whole Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in thoſe daies was alſo vicions? or becauſe <hi>Marcellinus, Liberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and 10. 22. denied <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> to be the true God and Eternal Life, therefore in thoſe daies <hi>Rome</hi> was no Church, but an <hi>Antichriſtian Synagogue,</hi> as you infer, <hi>Sect.</hi> 17. It follows as neceſſarily; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome Popes have been boys, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in thoſe times the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:37695:50"/>
conſiſted only of boys, and that there were neither men, women, nor children in the whole Church: as likewiſe, becauſe ſome Popes have been fools and knaves, that therefore at that time there were no wiſe nor honeſt men in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> To ſuch miſerable and ridiculous ſhifts are Heretiques driven, whoſe pride and obſtinacy is ſuch, that they will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther damn their own ſouls, then confeſs their errors.</p>
            <p>47. But by the way, Doctor, I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to obſerve, that thoſe Popes whom <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ronius</hi> complains of, in the places by you cited, (<hi>An. 908. nu.</hi> 5. and <hi>An. 931. nu.</hi> 1.) were but <hi>Pſeudo-Popes,</hi> not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully elected, but intruding into the <hi>Papacy</hi> by the power of the Marqueſſes of <hi>Tuſcany;</hi> his words are theſe, <hi>Mortuo</hi> Stephano <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia Widonis Tuſciae Marchionis, &amp; Maroziae matris, Sergii Pſeudo-Popae ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicto ſcorto</hi> Marozia <hi>filius, &amp;c. An.</hi> 931. where you find <hi>Sergius</hi> mention'd in your former citation, <hi>An.</hi> 908. but a Pſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>do-Pope; a meer Uſurper, and his Baſtard <hi>Iohn</hi> made Pope after <hi>Stephen,</hi> by the power <hi>Wido</hi> Marqueſs oſ <hi>Tuſcany:</hi> and a little after he has theſe words, <hi>It à planè tantae vires Marchionibus Tuſciae in urbe erant, ut pro arbitrio quos vellent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiali
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37695:50"/>
ſede deponerent, &amp; alios intrude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi> Here you ſee thoſe Princes ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in <hi>Rome,</hi> that they could diſpoſe, and ſet up what Popes they pleas'd. And I muſt deſire you, good Doctor, to take this alſo along with you, and that from <hi>Baronius,</hi> that in all the time of thoſe wicked, uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Schiſmatical Popes, Gods providence was over his Church, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe diſtracted and calamitous times, yet the <hi>Roman Church</hi> was preſerv'd free, both from Schiſm and Hereſie: For had you caſt your eye but a little farther, from <hi>nu.</hi> 5. to <hi>nu.</hi> 7. you ſhould have found theſe words, <hi>Cùm tanta iſta urgerent hoe ſaecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo mala, &amp; ſcandala increbreſcerent, tamen non eſt inventus qui eâ de causâ ſe ab ip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>â Eccleſiâ Romanâ abſcinderet Schiſmate, aut Hereſi eandem impugnaret, ſed omnes ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entium eidem Fidei vinculo, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedientiae foedere juncti perſiſtebant. An. 908. n.</hi> 7. You ſee then that <hi>Baronius</hi> could not ſee your conſequence, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there were ſome tyrannical, uſurping, and Schiſmatical Popes, therefore the whole Church of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt fail, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Schiſmatical: and I am ſomewhat confident, that D. <hi>Boughen</hi> was the firſt that ever diſcover'd this undiſcoverable conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:37695:51"/>48. Thoſe other words that you produce our of <hi>Baronius (An. 373. n.</hi> 21.) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you would make the world believe, that <hi>Baronius</hi> held an opinion, that the Pope by his own authority might make and alter Decrees in matters of Faith, as he pleas'd, are to be underſtood only thus, That the Pops, with the adviſe of his Biſhops, may in a private Councel for the peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs of the Church, till a General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel may be call'd, publiſh Decrees concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Doctrines of Faith; as alſo revoke, or alter ſuch Decrees, according as it ſhall be found neceſſary or convenient for the peace and unity of the Church: But that the Pope can of himſelf revoke or alter the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, determinations, or definitions of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councels concerning Doctrines of Faith, this <hi>Baronius</hi> never taught: he was too great a Scholar, and too good a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique to maintain ſuch a temerarious (I might ſay Heretical) Doctrine: and that this is the meaning of <hi>Baronius</hi> in that place, may appear by the context of his Narration, where he declares the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of S. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> to acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſce and ſubmit to the Decree of Pope <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus,</hi> (who then govern'd the Church) upon a ſuppoſition, that the Pope had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the <hi>Apollinarians</hi> to the Councel
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:37695:51"/>
at <hi>Rome,</hi> which not withſtanding was but a falſe pretence of the <hi>Apollinarians;</hi> where you may obſerve Doctor, that this bleſſed man was a Biſhop in the Eaſtern Church, and had formerly wrote ſharply againſt the <hi>Apollinarians;</hi> and yet upon a ſuppoſition, (though falſe) that they were reconcil'd to the Pope, and admitted to the Councel at <hi>Rome,</hi> he profeſt, that he would in all ſubmiſſion to the Pope, acquieſce, and not preſume to cenſure, or queſtion any Act or determination of the Pope, though it were concerning Doctrines of Faith.</p>
            <p>49. I have now paſt through your firſt <hi>anſwer,</hi> and purpoſed to have here conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; but I meet with an impertinent au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Doctor <hi>Lawd,</hi> which though I might juſtly have paſt by, without taking any notice thereof, as having undertaken an anſwer to D. <hi>Boughen,</hi> not D. <hi>Lawd,</hi> eſpecially ſince this of D. <hi>Lawd</hi> is already ſufficiently anſwer'd, <hi>Sect.</hi> 28. yet I have thought fit to make this further examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</p>
            <p>To the queſtion then; <hi>Where was your Church before Luther?</hi> D. <hi>Lawd</hi> anſwers, <hi>Where ours is now. Anſw.</hi> If by [<hi>ours</hi>] he means the particular Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I muſt confeſs his anſwer to be true; for
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:37695:52"/>
the particular Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a part or member af the Roman Catholike Church, and ſo were you before <hi>Luther;</hi> but with him you have apoſtatiz'd, and are fallen into Schiſm and He reſie, and inſtead of a Church, you are become an Heretical and Schiſmatical Congregation. <hi>Luther</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the whole Church, and thoſe, that ſoon after his Apoſtacy adhered to his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, followed him alſo in his Apoſtacy, they having been all members of that Church which <hi>Luther</hi> had forſaken. But this, you will ſay, was no ſeparation, but a reformation, for that <hi>D. Lawd</hi> drives at; <hi>One and the ſame Church ſtill</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>one in ſubſtance, but not one in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of ſtate and purity, your part of the ſame Church</hi> (by [your part] he means the Church of Rome) <hi>remaining in corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and our part of the ſame Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Reformation.</hi> Good God, how can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſociety of men, profeſſing themſelves Chriſtians, be one and the ſame Church, and that in ſubſtante with that, from which they ſeparated both in Faith and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? Or what can be a ſeparation, if this be not? If you have not ſeparated your ſelves from the Catholique Church, then were the <hi>Arrians, Neſtorians, Macedont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Pelagians,</hi> &amp;c. no Heretiques; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:37695:52"/>
were they ſeparated from the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church,</hi> but were only under <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> Do not you oppoſe and deny Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Faith, as antiently and as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally receiv'd by the Church, as thoſe that the <hi>Arrians, Neſtorians, Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Pelagians,</hi> &amp;c. oppos'd and denied? What difference can you make between <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> and <hi>Luther,</hi> in reſpect of their apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie? Did not <hi>Luther</hi> ſet himſelf againſt the whole world as well as <hi>Arrius?</hi> Did not the whole Chriſtian world, beſides your ſelves, upon your firſt Reformation (as you call it) deteſt your new Doctrines, and abhor your communion? Did not the pretended <hi>Greek Church</hi> it ſelf (into whoſe communion you were Petitioners to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted) condemn your new Doctrines as Heretical, and refuſe to receive you into their communion? Read the book entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Cenſura Orientalis Eccleſiae;</hi> and you ſhall there find the <hi>Greek Church</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining (and that againſt the Proteſtants) the Doctrine of <hi>ſeven Sacraments,</hi> cap. 7. of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, and real preſence of Chriſts body in the bleſſed Sacrarmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, c.</hi> 10. of <hi>auricular confeſſion, c.</hi> 11. of <hi>the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloudy propitiatory Sacrifice of the Maſs, c.</hi> 13. of <hi>free will, c.</hi> 18. of <hi>Traditions, c.</hi> 20. of <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> and <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:37695:53"/>
of Images, c.</hi> 21. Was there any one man in the whole world, that profeſt your Foctrine before <hi>Luther?</hi> and yet, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, yours was no ſeparation from the <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> but a <hi>Reformation,</hi> a bleſſed <hi>Reformation,</hi> that muſt neceſſarily juſtifie all former Hereſies, that ever were condemn'd, and all Heretiques and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques that ever ſeparated themſelves from Gods Church. To ſay no more, where is <hi>your ſucceſſion of Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors,</hi> which are eſſential to Gods Church? If the <hi>conſecration</hi> of your pretended Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops was never valid, then muſt alſo the <hi>Ordination</hi> of your pretended Prieſts be invalid; and it never yet could, nor ever can appear, that you had either Biſhop con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated, or Prieſt ordained, either lawfully or validly, ſince Queen <hi>Marye's</hi> days. But I am ſure there are moſt ſtrong and preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant arguments for the contrary. I deny not, but that perchance there might be ſome Prieſts ordained validly (though ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly) by that Apoſtate Biſhop of <hi>Spala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> in the time of his ſtay in <hi>England;</hi> but what is that to a <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> of Prieſts and Biſhops?</p>
            <p>I have now done with the firſt <hi>anſwer,</hi> and paſs to the ſecond; which becauſe I find to conſiſt principally of ſcurrilityes,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:37695:53"/>
perſonal and malicious invectives, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions of former <hi>fallacies,</hi> my reply will be the ſhorter, ſince I ſhall in many things refer the Reader to my former an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, and take notice here only of that which I ſhall find to be new matter.</p>
            <p>50. And here at the very firſt entrance I meet with an old fallacy, a ridiculous ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument already anſwered, Sect. 5. to which I muſt refer the Reader. I will here add this only; That before S. <hi>Peter</hi> tranſlated his <hi>Chair</hi> from <hi>Antioch</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church might be properly called the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> which ever ſince has been called the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will be, until S. <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſor ſhall tranſlate his Chair to ſome other place.</p>
            <p>51. After this follows a moſt notorious falſhood, viz. <hi>That in the time of</hi> S. Hilary <hi>of Poicteurs, there was at Rome no Church, no communion of Saints,</hi> She <hi>and thoſe in communion with her, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and complied with</hi> Arrius: This is moſt apparently falſe by the Records of all Hiſtories; for at that time the <hi>Weſterne Church</hi> was nothing ſo much infected with <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> as the <hi>Eaſtern,</hi> beſides S. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> in that place by you cited Sect. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. has not ſo much as named the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore has not in particular exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:37695:54"/>
it from the Catholique Church. But from thoſe words of the Father [<hi>caeteris extra Gallias</hi>] you would prove, that all the world beſides France was out of the Catholique Church; for (ſay you) <hi>There was then no communion with Rome, unleſs it can be prov'd, that Rome was in France,</hi> Sect. 23. But pray tell me Doctor, Was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria</hi> and <hi>Sardinia</hi> more in <hi>France,</hi> then <hi>Rome?</hi> and yet you here confeſs, that at the very ſame time thoſe were Catholike and Orthodox Churches; ſo that it muſt neceſſarily follow, either that <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Sardinia</hi> were in France, or elſe that ſome other Churches, beſides France, were Catholique and Orthodox, and if ſo, why not Rome? eſpecially ſince that Father did not in particular charge <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> more then <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Sardinia;</hi> ſo that if you by thoſe general words of the Father will exclude <hi>Rome,</hi> I may alſo as well exclude <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Sardinia</hi> from the Catholique Church: Wherefore you have forc't your ſelf to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret thoſe words of the Father, as I have done, Sect. 34. or elſe you muſt unſay what you have ſaid, and deny <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Sardinia</hi> to have been at that time Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and Orthodox Churches, unleſs you can prove, that <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Sardinia</hi> are in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:37695:54"/>52. Hitherto then you have ſhewed no Church at all diſtinct from the Roman Church in any age, though you were pleas'd to ſay Sect. 3. of this ſecond anſwer, <hi>That your learning is ſuch, that you doe know ſuch a Church, and your charity ſuch, that you have ſhews it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems you ſhewed it ſo well, that M. <hi>T. B.</hi> was thereby fully ſatisfied, that the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> never was, nor can be diſtinct from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and has thereupon imbraced her communion, and is by Gods grace, become a good <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique.</hi> Thus has God been pleaſed to produce good out of evil, to work his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs out of your ignorance, and to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him by your weakneſs.</p>
            <p>53. I paſs by your ſcurrilous ſpeeches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt M. <hi>T. B.</hi> as <hi>your comparing him to</hi> Seneca's <hi>wives fool; your charging him for not being able to ſearch the Scriptures, Councels, and Fathers, to diſcover the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity and ſucceſſion of your Doctrine there</hi> (where no man ever yet did, or can diſcover it) I will only ſay this, that M. <hi>T. B.</hi> has ſhewn more wit and judgment in one line, then you have in all your Pamphlet, and has ſaid more in one ſentence, then you, or all the Rabble of your Sect can anſwer in an age. But let us ſee how you
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:37695:55"/>
prove the antiquity of your Doctrine.</p>
            <p>54. <hi>The Doctrine</hi> (you ſay) <hi>of the Church of</hi> England <hi>is clear in your Book of Common-Prayer, as for the poſitive part; and in your book of Articles,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in much is <hi>Negattve. Anſw.</hi> A very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Doctrine then it muſt be, your Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> being made not much above 100. years ſince, viz. 29. <hi>May</hi> 1549. in the reign of K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth; and your Book of <hi>Articles</hi> not much above half an hundred. But was your book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> intended for a <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> or for publique <hi>Service and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion?</hi> Is there any point of Faith or Doctrine abſolutely declar'd and defin'd there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> You will ſay, perchance, that in the three <hi>Creeds</hi> are contain'd divers De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratious and definitions of Faith; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it, but thoſe <hi>Creeds</hi> are not inſerted there meerly as definitions of Faith, with a precept under a curſe, that all ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve whatſoever is there declard, but as parts of your <hi>Publique Service,</hi> that by frequent repetition thereof, the vulgar people might know the principal points of Faith neceſſary for ſalvation, I deny not; but ſome Doctrines may be deducible thence, though nothing poſitively declared, it being a book which belongs rather to the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37695:55"/>
Diſcipline, then Doctrine of your pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Church.</p>
            <p>55. <hi>The poſitive Doctrine,</hi> you ſay, <hi>of your Church contained in that Book, was ever profeſſed, and is viſible in all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Writers. Anſw.</hi> I confeſs, that moſt (if not all) of the Doctrines deducible thence, <hi>were ever profeſſed, and are viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all Catholique Writers,</hi> becauſe they are the Doctrines of the <hi>Roman Catholike Church,</hi> whence you have borrowed them, as you have your whole book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf, only you have taken the ſacrilegious boldneſs to expunge out of both what your private phancies would not admit: but if you can ſhew any one of your <hi>negative</hi> or <hi>poſitive</hi> Doctrines contain'd in your book of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi> and which is oppoſite to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in any one Catholique Writer, Father, or Councel, from the time of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to <hi>Luthers</hi> Apoſtaſie, I here profeſs before all the world, that I will then become a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> my ſelf, or whatſoever elſe you will command me to be.</p>
            <p>56. But whereas you ſay, That <hi>the moſt skilful</hi> (of the Roman Catholique Party) <hi>are not able to ſhew a ſucceſſion of men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Doctrine of the Church of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37695:56"/>
Rome, in the first 700. years of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi> I am ſo amaz'd, that I know not whether I ſhould charge you with <hi>groſs ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,</hi> or <hi>helliſh malice:</hi> In plain terms, you muſt be either a moſt ignorant ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, or a malicious deceiver. Is it poſſible that you ſhould obtrude ſuch a notorious falſhood to the world, and not bluſh? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly you never read the Fathers, nor Councels, nor therein examin'd the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Doctrine and practiſe of the Church, or if you have (as you pretend) your judgment is not ſufficient to underſtand them; or elſe malice and obſtinacy hath ſo blinded you, that you cannot ſee it there, as the malicious and obſtinate Jews could not ſee our bleſſed Saviours Divinity through ſo many ſtupendious miracles. The Sun it ſelf was never ſo clear at noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, as the ſucceſſion of the Doctrine of the Church of Rome, and of men profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame, not only for the firſt 700. years of Chriſtianity, but from the time of the Apoſtles to this preſent day. Has it not been already clearly ſhewn by divers learned Catholique Writers, by you yet un-anſwer'd? Has not <hi>Bellarmine, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Peron,</hi> D. <hi>Stratford, &amp;c.</hi> moſt evidently manifeſted it to the world? Were I not confin'd within the narrow
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:37695:56"/>
precincts of a <hi>Reply,</hi> I could moſt plainly demonſtrate it my ſelf; but it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a far larger volume then I have now time or opportunity to compoſe: It is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for me, ſince you have appealed to the firſt 500. years after our Saviours birth, that I have proved (Sect. 44.) that the Doctrine of thoſe times is not different from, but the very ſame with the preſent Doctrine of the <hi>Roman Catholike Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>57. Your Church (of England) you ſay, <hi>has been viſible ſince the firſt or ſecond Converſion, though not alwayes under Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Anſw.</hi> Which you mean by the firſt or ſecond Converſion, I know not; but from the time of her laſt Converſion by S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Monk (which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly reputed her third converſion) for almoſt 1000. years together, you were an apparent viſible part of the Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique; but when you began your bleſſed <hi>Reformation,</hi> you then ceaſt to be a Church, or a part of the <hi>Catholique Church.</hi> For in K. <hi>Hen.</hi> eight's dayes you began your Schiſm, ſeparating your ſelves from the communion of your holy Mother the Church of Rome, and the Biſhop there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the common Paſtor of Chriſts Church; and in K. <hi>Edw.</hi> the Sixths Reign your Schiſm begat Hereſie, and under this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:37695:57"/>
               <hi>Reformation</hi> you have ever ſince conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</p>
            <p>But now Doctor, where are your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Biſhops? what is become of your book of <hi>Common-Prayer?</hi> who now ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to your 39. Articles? You cannot reaſonably deny, but thoſe, who have late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reformed you, had more authority and reaſon for it, then you had to reform the whole Church, or to cenſure Doctrines of Faith univerſally taught by Gods Church, and receiv'd as ſuch by all your Fore-fathers, from the time of <hi>Englands</hi> converſion to the Chriſtian Faith, till after <hi>Luthers</hi> apoſtaſie: You conſidered not, when under pretence of Reformation you forſook the whole Church, that you did but leave a patern to your Succeſſors, how they alſo, when they ſhould think fit, might for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake you, and reform this your bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, as by Gods juſt judgments they have lately done: For I am ſure they walk by the ſame Rule of Scripture, and are as competent Judges, and as able interpreters thereof, as ever you were, or can be; only they are not ſo tyrannical as you were, who forced men againſt their conſciences to ſubſcribe to your Doctrine and Diſcipline, which according to your own principles, might be erroneous and ſuperſtitious.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:37695:57"/>58. But you ſay Sect. 9. That you never read in <hi>Fathers</hi> or <hi>Councels, That to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with Rome, is either a ſure, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny token of a good Catholique. Anſw.</hi> Then you never read S. <hi>Hieroms</hi> 57 Epiſt. to Pope <hi>Damaſus,</hi> where you might have ſeen theſe words, <hi>Ego Beatitudini tuae, id eſt Cathedrae</hi> Petri, <hi>commumione conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ior, ſuper illam</hi> Petram <hi>aedificatam Eccleſiam ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io,</hi> Mat. 16. 18. <hi>quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> extra hanc Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum agnum comederit, prophanus est; ſi quis in Arca No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non fuerit, peribit reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante diluvio; quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tecum non colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, ſpargit; Hoc eſt, qui Chriſti non est, Anti-chriſti eſt.</hi> I am (ſaith S. <hi>Hierom) joyned in communion to your Holineſs, that is, to</hi> Peters Chair, <hi>upon that Rock I know the Church to be built, whoſoever out of this Houſe eats the Ldmb, is prophane; whoſoever ſhall not be in</hi> Noahs <hi>Ark, ſhall periſh in the Deluge; he that gathers not with thee, ſcatters, that is, he that is not of Chriſt, is of Anti-chriſt.</hi> Theſe are S. <hi>Hieroms</hi> own words, by which it is moſt plain, that he that is not in communion with S. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, with the Church and Biſhop of Rome, is out of Gods Church, and therefore no Catholique.</p>
            <p>Neither did you ever read S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s Funeral Oration on the death of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:37695:58"/>
               <hi>Satyrus,</hi> where you might have found theſe words, <hi>Advocavit ad ſe Epiſcopum, &amp;c. percontatuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex eo eſt, utrumnam cum Epiſcopis Catholicis, hoc eſt, cum Romana Eccleſia conveniret. He call'd unto him a Biſhop, and aked him, whether he were in communion with the Catholique Biſhops, that is, with the Church of Rome.</hi> And here take notice, Doctor, that this [<hi>Hoc eſt,</hi> that is] as likewiſe that [<hi>id eſt,</hi> and <hi>hoc eſt</hi>] in the former citation out of S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> are the Fathers own interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, not mine.</p>
            <p>Had you read S. <hi>Auguſtin's</hi> 162. Epiſtle, you might have diſcovered theſe words there: <hi>Hic (Caecilianus) contemnere potu it, &amp;c. He</hi> (Caecilianus) <hi>might deſpiſe the conſpiring multitude of his enemies, when he perceiv'd himſelf to be united to the Church of Rome, where the principality of the Apoſtolique Chair ever flouriſht, by communicatory letters.</hi> Theſe three learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Fathers, and glorious lights of Gods church were <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taneans,</hi> though S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> died in the fourth century after <hi>Chriſts</hi> birth, and S. <hi>Hierom</hi> and S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> in the fift.</p>
            <p>Had you read S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cond Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Cornelius, li.</hi> 4. who lived in the year of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 250. you might have found
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:37695:58"/>
theſe words; <hi>Scripſisti etiam, ut exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum, &amp;c. You wrote alſo unto me, to ſend a copy of thoſe Letters to</hi> Cornelius <hi>our Colleague, that he laying aſide all care, might know that you are in communion with him, that is, with the Catholique Church.</hi> This [<hi>Hoc eſt,</hi> that is,] alſo is not my addition, but S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> own words. It ſeems you were a ſtranger to S. <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus</hi>'s Doctrine, who liv'd in the year of Chriſt 180. which is this; <hi>Ad hanc enim</hi> (Romanam) <hi>Eccleſiam propter po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiorem principalitatem neceſſe est om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem convenire Eccleſiam, hoc est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os qui ſunt undi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fideles; It is neceſſary that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Church, that is, all the faithful from all parts, ſhould range themſelves to this Church</hi> (of Rome) <hi>for its more powerful principality, li. 3. c.</hi> 3. And now <hi>Doctor,</hi> what can you ſay? Methinks you look ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what black upon it; you muſt withall take notice, that all theſe Fathers liv'd within the firſt 500. years to which you have appealed, and there is not one of all theſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies but is plainly againſt you, evidently proving it not only a ſure, but a neceſſary and eſſential token of a good Catholique, to communicate with the Church of Rome. A thouſand teſtimonies more might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, but theſe are ſufficient to publiſh
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:37695:59"/>
D. <hi>Boughens</hi> ignorance to the world. I thought it not impertinent to add one teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony more (in confirmation of this, and what I ſaid before, Sect. 32. of <hi>John</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Hormiſda,</hi> who about the beginning of the century, viz. <hi>An.</hi> 514. was elected Pope, that thereby the communion of the <hi>Greek Church</hi> with the <hi>Roman,</hi> and her ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Apoſtolique Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> may plainly appear. <hi>Promittentes in ſeque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te tempore, &amp;c. We promiſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after not to commemorate thoſe in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred myſteries, who have been ſecluded from the communion of the Catholique Church, that is, who conſent not fully with the Sea Apoſtolique.</hi> Here is the opinion of the great Patriarch of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> above a 1100. years ſince, That thoſe who were ſeparated from the Sea Apoſtolique, were out of the communion of the Catholique Church: and by this it appears how true your following words are, viz. <hi>That faith which we receiv'd from the Apoſtles, and Councels, and Fathers, we keep whole and undefiled, without alteration, addition, or diminution.</hi> What but a ſhameleſs man could have the face to publiſh ſuch a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious falſhood to the world? By this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears alſo how evidently falſe that ſaying
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:37695:59"/>
of yours is (at leaſt as you apply it) in the beginning of your 11. Sect. viz. <hi>That this National Church is as much Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and Apoſtolique as can be deſired.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs, this National Church (that is, thoſe that preſerve the antient Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and Apoſtolique Faith, and keep themſelves within the communion of the holy <hi>Catholique Church</hi>) is, God be prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as much Catholique and Apoſtolique, as can be deſired: but I am ſure, thoſe of your Congregation, or pretended church, are neither Catholique or Apoſtolique, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to forſake the communion of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church,</hi> and the Doctrines and Traditions of the Apoſtles, be to be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique and Apoſtolique, as I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy abundantly proved. And that Rule which you cite out of <hi>Vincent Lyrinenſ.</hi> in the later end of your 10. Sect. [<hi>Quod u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, quod ſemper, quod ab omnibus, &amp;c. That which hath been believed in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, at all times, by all the Fathers, that is truly Catholique</hi>] will riſe up in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt you. By this Rule you have condemn'd your ſelf of Schiſm and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; for your Doctrine has been ſo far from being believed in all places, at all times, and by all the Fathers, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for you to ſhew any one place, any
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:37695:60"/>
one time, or any one Father; nay, any one man before <hi>Luthers</hi> Apoſtaſie, that maintain'd the Doctrines which are now compriſed in your <hi>Book of Articles:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can you produce any one perſon at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time or place, that held any one point of Doctrine, wherein you diſſent from, and oppoſe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> except ſuch only, as were noted by the Church for Innovators in Religion, and condemn'd for Heretiques.</p>
            <p>59. And wheras you are pleas'd to inſult over Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> Sect. 12. in theſe high and daring ſpeeches. [<hi>Is not all true? Refute it if you can: deny it, if you have the face</hi>] I, or any reaſonable man, may have the face to tell you, that you here ſhow your ſelfe to be very ignorant, impudent, and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. For the Doctrine of that part of your 19. <hi>Article.</hi> viz. [<hi>That the viſible Church of Chriſt is a congregation of faithfull me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the which the pure Word of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, according to Chriſt's ordinance, in all thoſe things that of neceſſity are requiſite to the ſame</hi>] Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> never denied, or queſtion'd; But denies that this doctrine of your 19. <hi>Article</hi> can conſiſt with your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, who hold, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a true Church, a member of the Church
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:37695:60"/>
Catholique, though according to divers of your <hi>Articles</hi> cited by Mr. <hi>T. B. n.</hi> 3. She neither preaches the pure Word of God, nor duly adminiſters the Sacraments, no, not in all thoſe things, that of neceſſity are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the ſame. For how can that be eſſentially a part of the Catholique Church, which obſerves not that which is eſſentiall to the Catholique Church, as is the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the pure Word of God, and the due adminiſtration of the Sacraments, according to that definition of the Church in your 19. <hi>Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, how can you vindicate that Church from hereſie, that for Doctrines of Faith neceſſary to ſalvation teaches <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous fables? Art.</hi> 31. Or that Sacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly robs the <hi>Laity</hi> of Chriſt's bloud<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with which you charge the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> Sect. 11. <hi>of your firſt Anſwer:</hi> Or that maintaines Doctrines repugnant to plaine words of Scripture? Sect. 24. <hi>ib.</hi> Or that erres in Doctrine of faith, as you tax the Church of <hi>Rome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Sect. 14. of your <hi>ſecond Anſwer.</hi> Or that gives divine worſhip to Images and Reliques, wherewith you charge the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Sect. 34. <hi>ib.?</hi> Can any Church be <hi>blaſphemous, ſacrilegious, idolatrous, repugnant in her Doctrines to plaine words of Scripture, erroneus in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:37695:61"/>
Doctrines of Faith,</hi> and yet not be heretical, but continue ſtill <hi>eſſentially</hi> a true Church?</p>
            <p>But becauſe you are pleas'd to extend your Charity beyond Reaſon towards the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I will not quarrell with you about it; onely I muſt take notice of the Argument, which you bring to prove it. <hi>God</hi> (ſay you) <hi>blames the Church of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamos for enduring the ſeat of Satan with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her Dioceſſe, as alſo for holding that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>didous Doctrine of the Nicolaitans, and yet grants her to be a Church. Anſw.</hi> Herein you are much miſtaken, <hi>Doctor,</hi> for God blames not the Church, but the <hi>Angell</hi> of the Church of <hi>Pergamos;</hi> which by many Catholique Expoſitors both Ancient and Moderne; as alſo by divers of your owne <hi>Sect</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> is interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>The biſhop of the Church.</hi> If the Church of <hi>Pergamos</hi> had held the Doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> She had bin Hereticall, and conſequently no Church: but it was the Biſhop, not the Church, that was hereticall. And if God may charge the Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Pergamos</hi> with Hereſie, and yet grant <hi>Pergamos</hi> to be a true Church; why may not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> continue a true Church, though the Biſhop thereof fall into hereſie?</p>
            <p>60. your taking the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:37695:61"/>
maiming the bleſſed Sacrament. Sect. 13. has been fully anſwer'd already. Sect. 18. 19. and. Sect. 41.</p>
            <p>61. But the Doctor is very hot in prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Church muſt erre with her Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; and therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was no Church, when her Biſhops were he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall. <hi>Such as the Biſhop is</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>ſuch is the Church preſumed to be.</hi> Anſw. I know none but Dr. <hi>Boughen,</hi> that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver guilty of ſo ſilly a Preſumption. But S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> Authority is urg'd to prove it, who ſayes, <hi>that as the Biſhop is in the Church, ſo is the Church in the Biſhop.</hi> I conſeſſe, I find in S. <hi>Cyprian. (Epiſt. lib. 4. Ep. 9.)</hi> theſe words; <hi>Christiani ſunt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae &amp; plebs Sacerdoti adunata, &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtori ſuo grex adhaerens; unde ſcire debes, Epiſcopum in Eccleſia eſſe &amp; Eccleſiam in Epiſcopo. Chriſtians are a Church, and Common people, united to the Preiſt, and a Flock adhering to its Pastor; whence you muſt know, that the Biſhop is in the Church, and the Church in the Biſhop.</hi> What is all this to the purpoſe? The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is in the Church, as a King is in his Kingdome, or a Generall in his Army; and the Church likewiſe is in the Biſhop, not <hi>formally,</hi> but <hi>communicativè;</hi> all the particular members thereof being in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:37695:62"/>
with the Biſhop, as their <hi>Head.</hi> And this is all that can be gather'd from thoſe words of the <hi>Father.</hi> Since then the Church cannot be <hi>Formally</hi> in the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> but onely by way of communion, ſubjection, govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Diſcipline; why may not the Church be Catholique, though the Biſhop be Hereticall?</p>
            <p>But from this falſe ground the Doctor will proſecute his old fallacy, and will ſtill be endeavouring to prove, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could not be Catholique, when the Biſhops thereof were heretiques. Sect, 19. <hi>All Heretiques</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>while ſuch, both themſelves and all that ſide with them, are ſecluded from Eccleſiaſtical communion eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way. But divers Popes were Heretiques or Schiſmatiques; therefore the Church of Rome while her Biſhops were heretical was in an ill caſe. Anſw.</hi> Is not this a ſine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from thoſe Premiſes? what form or conſequence is this here of a Syllogiſm? And if the concluſion did follow out of thoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, what were this to the purpoſe? The Church may be in an ill caſe, when the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is in hereſie, yet not Hereticall. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold another argument to prove the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> not Catholique: <hi>When all Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Acts were voyd, the Church could not poſſibly be Catholike. But when the Biſhops
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:37695:62"/>
were Heretiques, all Epiſcopall Acts were void; therefore the Church could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be Catholique. Anſw.</hi> This conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is much like the other: <hi>All the Acts of Heretical Biſhops are void; therefore the Church cannot poſſibly be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique;</hi> as if the Faith of the Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on the Acts of the Biſhop. But a confirmation thereof is brought from S. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries</hi> teſtimony, who <hi>profeſſeth,</hi> as you ſay. <hi>That (in theſe Weſtern parts) there was in his time no Chriſtian communion, but in France. Anſw.</hi> You do well to put thoſe words [<hi>in theſe Western parts</hi>] in a parentheſis, for they are yours, not S. <hi>Hilaries;</hi> as may appear by his words by you cited, Sect. 23. where thoſe words [<hi>caeteris extra Gallias</hi>] may comprehend the Eaſtern as well as the Weſtern Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And if you read Eccleſiaſtical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, you ſhall find, that in S. <hi>Hilaries</hi> time the Eaſtern Churches were far more infected with <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> then the Weſtern.</p>
            <p>62. Beſides, you may remember, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, that in the beginning of this ſecond anſwer, you confeſt, that in S. <hi>Hilaries</hi> time, at that very time when Rome (as you falſly ſay) was <hi>Arrian, Sardinia</hi> was a Catholique and Orthodox Church: How can that agree with this which you here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:37695:63"/>
to prove out of S. <hi>Hilary?</hi> Was not <hi>Sardinia</hi> part of the Weſtern Church? How then could all the Weſtern parts be excluded from <hi>Chriſtian communion,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides France, when <hi>Sardinia,</hi> which is in theſe Weſtern parts, was (as your ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs) a Catholique and Orthodox Church? How can theſe two poſſibly conſiſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? It ſeems you have forgot your ſelf. <hi>Oportet mendacem eſſe memorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>60. After all the other Popes. <hi>Faelix</hi> is brought in for communicating with <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Zozomen</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to prove, that therefore <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf was then accounted <hi>Arrian.</hi> What then, ſays <hi>Socrates?</hi> that <hi>Liberius</hi> was baniſh't for his conſtancy in defending the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Faith againſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and that <hi>Faelix</hi> was appointed to ſucceed him in the <hi>Papacy,</hi> who was, <hi>Arrianae Sectae addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus:</hi> but there is not one word there of Rome's being <hi>Arrian. (Socrat. li. 2. c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.) And if <hi>Faelix</hi> did perchance ſometimes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Arrian Faction, yet was it before he was elected Pope, not afterwards; as appears plainly by <hi>Sozomen</hi> in the very place by you cited, <hi>li. 4. c.</hi> 10. Liberius <hi>Eccleſiae Romanae Epiſcopatu privatus eſt, cui praefuïtur</hi> Faelix <hi>illius Cleri Diaconus, quem aiunt Fidei Concilii Nicaeni ſemper
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:37695:63"/>
conſenſiſſe, &amp; omnino, quantum pertinebat ad Religionem, reprehenſione caruiſſe.</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius (ſaith he) <hi>was depriv'd of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of the Roman Church, to which</hi> Faelix, <hi>a Deacon of that Clergy, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaid to have alwayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Faith of the Nicene Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and was never blameable for any thing that concerned Religion.</hi> Theſe are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words of <hi>Sozomen,</hi> and in the very ſame place cited by the Doctor. Nothing there concerning <hi>Faelix</hi> or <hi>Rome's</hi> being <hi>Arrian.</hi> Thus the Reader may ſee how fraudulently the <hi>Doctor</hi> has dealt with the world.</p>
            <p>Well, but <hi>Faelix or dained divers Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> what then? muſt he therefore be an Arrian himſelf? or muſt he neceſſarily know them to be ſuch?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But he communicated with Arrians;</hi> and muſt he therefore be an Arrian? Do not Catholiques at this time communicate with Heretiques in <hi>England, France, Germany, &amp;c.</hi> in outward converſation and civil commerce, though not in their Hereſie? and you neither have prov'd, nor ever can prove, that <hi>Faelix</hi> communicated with the <hi>Arrians</hi> in their heretical and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Doctrine, but in outward converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only, which is, and ever was lawful for any Catholique.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:37695:64"/>61. To paſs by your impertinent diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction between a <hi>profeſt</hi> and a <hi>cloſe</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, as being nothing to the purpoſe: I come to your other paſſage, wherein you ſay, and cite ſome <hi>Canons</hi> for it; <hi>That the communion of the Church is estimated by communicating with the Biſhop, and if any, whether Prieſt, or other, ſhall ſever themſelves from the Canonical Biſhop, they are cenſur'd to be Heretiques. Anſw.</hi> This is to be underſtood when the Biſhop is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, and keeps himſelf within the communion of the Catholique Church; but if the Biſhop be heretical, and the Church ſhall communicate with him in his Hereſie, the Church alſo becomes hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, be the Biſhop thereof a profeſt or cloſe Heretique, it matters not: but by this your own Rule you muſt confeſs your ſelves He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques, becauſe you did originally ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver your ſelves from your Canonical Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Biſhops, and followed your owne, and other mens new inventions; and when all your pretended biſhops were heretical, you communicated with them and their hereſies.</p>
            <p>62. But the biſhop may be either a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt or cloſe Heretique, and yet the Church may be Catholique: and this your ſelf expreſly grant in your following Sect. 22.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:37695:64"/>
where you ſay, <hi>That you believe that the King of England, and Arch-biſhop of Cauterbury, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ither, or both of them, may be Heretiques, and this Church not ſo; ſince it is not their being, but our comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that makes us heretical.</hi> Herein you have fully contradicted your ſelf, and granted whatſoever I have ſaid concerning this point: For if the Church of England may be Catholique, though both King and Metropolitan thereof be Heretiques, why may not the Church of Rome be Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, though the biſhop thereof be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical?</p>
            <p>63. <hi>But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>if all our Biſhops be of the ſame Religion with them, this Church is in an ill caſe. Anſw.</hi> I ſay ſo too; yet it may be Catholique. All your pretended biſhops may be heretical (as they were all for about theſe 100. years together laſt paſt) and yet there may be a Catholique Church in England. It is poſſible that the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar members of each Dioceſs may not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with their biſhop in his Hereſie; and then, according to your own ſaying, they are not heretical. The inferiour Prieſts and people may preſerve their faith, though all the biſhops fall from it: but what is all this to the purpoſe? Were ever all the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that were ſubject to the Patriarchal
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:37695:65"/>
Sea of Rome, at one and the ſame time, Heretiques? I ſuppoſe, no man beſides your ſelf was ever poſſeſt with ſuch a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous imagination. What if your Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> alone had been an Heretique, and all the other biſhops with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Province Catholique? will you therefore conclude, that the particular <hi>Church</hi> or Dioceſs of <hi>Canterbury</hi> muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily have been heretical? If you ſay ſo, you plainly contradict your ſelf, who even now ſaid, that it is not the Kings or Arch-biſhops being heretical, but our complying with them, that makes us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, Sect. 22.</p>
            <p>64. But the Doctor purſues this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cloſe, and endeavours to prove, that <hi>when the King and Prieſt joyn together, it hath a ſtrange influence upon the people, for good or bad. Anſw.</hi> What then? muſt the people therefore of neceſſity be good or bad, according as the King and Prieſt are? cannot Gods grace overcome this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and preſerve the people from infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? but you ſay; <hi>When King</hi> Ahaz, <hi>and</hi> Urijah <hi>the Priest profeſſed I dolatry, though many good men were reſident among them, yet was the City and people account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heretical. Anſw.</hi> Firſt, it appears not by the Text, that they were ſo accompted.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:37695:65"/>
Secondly, if they were accompted heretical, does it herefore neceſſarily follow, that they were ſo? Does truth and falſhood de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on the opinions of men? if ſo, then every man in his own opinion would be Catholique, and all the world beſides, that concur not with him in his judgment, would be Heretiques. It is not neceſſary that every one muſt be good or bad, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, or heretique, according as ſome men (perchance) out of error, either in doctrine or fact, ſhall eſteem him: but what if that city and people were (not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted, but) truly and really heretical, muſt it therefore always follow, that when the King and Prieſt are heretical, the city and people muſt of neceſſity be ſo too? What if <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Emperor, and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius</hi> the biſhop? What if <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alens</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxius</hi> by joyning together in hereſie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew many, partly by power, pardly by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample from the Catholique Faith; does it therefore always neceſſarily follow, that when the Prince and Prieſt joyn in hereſie, the people alſo muſt be heretical? Muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing come to paſs, becauſe it may come to paſs? No, Doctor, the young Sophiſters will tell you, that, <hi>à poſſe &amp; eſſe non valet argumentum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>65. And whereas you ſay, that under
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:37695:66"/>
King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the Religion of the church was judged of by the Governours: I anſwer, that the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of this Nation (not of the church, for 'tis not the Religion of the Prince, but the profeſſion of the antient Catholique Faith, that conſtitutes a church) was judged of, not by the Governours, but by the Lawes that were made in K. <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. and Queen <hi>Maryes</hi> daies reſpectively, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to eſtabliſh a new upſtart Religion, never before heard of in the world, or to re-eſtabliſh the antient Catholique Faith: So that in K. <hi>Edw.</hi> VI. days the <hi>Nation</hi> might be ſaid to be heretical, but the Church was even at that time Catholike, otherwiſe it could not have been a church; and in Q. <hi>Maryes</hi> daies both church and Nation were Catholique. But you cannot prove that ever the <hi>Roman Nation,</hi> much leſs the <hi>Roman Church</hi> was heretical, ſince their firſt converſion to the Chriſtian faith. And if the Pope, and with him all the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Italy</hi> had at the ſame time forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Catholique faith, yet the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> might ſtill have retain'd her prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of being the Mother church, and Head of all particular churches in the world. And though the Pope might have forfeited all his Eccleſiaſtical power and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:37695:66"/>
Juriſdiction, and ſo ceaſt to be Head of the church, yet the right of S. <hi>Peters Chair</hi> had always remained in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> for ſince the biſhop is not the church formally, nor the church formally in the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, the church cannot formally erre with the biſhop, neither muſt the church formally taken, be there fore heretical, becauſe the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop thereof is ſo. Now, I hope, I have done with this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edious and frivolous argument.</p>
            <p>65. That the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> impoſes a new ſenſe on the articles of the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeds,</hi> is a meer calumny, ſpoken <hi>gratis,</hi> without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny colour or ſhew of proof. That the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and you agree in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not in the Expoſition, is true; The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> following the Expoſition of the Univerſal Tradition and practiſe of the church, and you your new phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and heretical Expoſition: but though you did agree with the Roman Church in the Expoſition, as well as in the letter, yet could you not be excus'd from hereſie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you oppoſe other Doctrines of Faith that are not contain'd in the three <hi>Creeds:</hi> for not all points of faith, that are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for all ſorts of men to be believed, are comprehended in the <hi>three Creeds,</hi> either joyntly, or ſeverally.</p>
            <p>66. And whereas you charge the <hi>Church</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:37695:67"/>
of <hi>Rome,</hi> with impoſing a new <hi>Creed</hi> of <hi>Pius</hi> 4. upon the church, againſt a canon of the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> I anſwer, firſt, That which you mean is but a profeſſion of Faith, wherein are contained certain Doctrines of faith that are not expreſly comprehended in the <hi>Creeds.</hi> It can no more properly be called a <hi>Creed,</hi> then your book of <hi>Articles,</hi> which is your Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith; and as not all, but ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain perſons only amongſt you, were bound by your Statutes to ſubſcribe to that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion;</hi> ſo likewiſe not every man, but ſome certain perſons only are bound to ſubſcribe to the other. Secondly, that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> was agreed upon by the whole <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel,</hi> and confirm'd by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> 4. It was neither compos'd, nor commanded by the Pope alone, but by him joyntly wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the <hi>Councel.</hi> Thirdly, there is not one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of that <hi>Profeſſion</hi> contrary or repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to any one article of the former <hi>Creeds:</hi> and although this had been a new <hi>Creed,</hi> as you call it, yet had it not been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any canon of the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> that <hi>Councel,</hi> at the moſt, for bidding only private perſons to ſet forth, or publiſh any <hi>Creed,</hi> that ſhould contain in it any Doctrine contrary to any article of belief in thoſe former <hi>Creeds,</hi> Neither indeed
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:37695:67"/>
could the church in the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> debar the church in future ages of that power and authority, which the church in former ages aſſumed and exerciſed. Why ſhould it be more unlawful for the church aſſembled in the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> to ſet forth a new form of <hi>Profeſſion of Faith,</hi> then it was for the church aſſembled in the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinople?</hi> No <hi>Councel</hi> can rob the church of that power which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath given her. And by this Profeſſion of Faith the <hi>Roman Church</hi> has neither alter'd the letter, nor ſenſe of former <hi>Creeds;</hi> though <hi>you dare be bold to ſay, She has ſtrangely alter'd the ſenſe.</hi> I confeſs, you are bold to ſay any thing, but you have prov'd nothing.</p>
            <p>67. And whereas you ſay, <hi>you take the Rule of Faith in the literal ſenſe,</hi> let us ſee (to give but one inſtance) ſince you make Scripture the ſole Rule of your faith, whether you take thoſe words of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Mat. 26. 26. Mar.</hi> 14. 22. and <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. 19. in the literal ſenſe. Our B Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour there takes Bread and Wine, and ſayes, <hi>This is my Body which is given (or broken) for you; This is my Bloud which is ſhed for you;</hi> which you thus interpret, <hi>This is a ſign only of my Body, and this is a ſign only of my Bloud.</hi> You deny, that
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:37695:68"/>
the bread and wine which our B. Saviour took and bleſt, was truly and ſubſtantially converted into his body and bloud, and are not aſham'd to ſay, that the doctrine of <hi>Tranſubstantiation</hi> is <hi>repugnant to the plain words of Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let all the world judg, whether herein you take the Rule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Faith in the literal ſenſe. It is much more plain, that you go againſt the very letter of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the expoſitions of the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Councels, the antient and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal practiſe of the whole church, which alwayes adored the <hi>B. Sacrament,</hi> after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, with divine worſhip.</p>
            <p>68. In Sect. 29. I meet with another ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and impertinent diſtinction, <hi>between errour in Faith, and errour in matters of Faith;</hi> as if errours in Faith, and errours in matters of Faith were not all one. They have hitherto been eſteemed all one, and that by thoſe who have been far beyond you both in learning and judgment; though your ſharp underſtanding be able to divide, and put a difference between them.</p>
            <p>69. Much like to this is that ſaying of yours Sect. 30. <hi>Every violation of the Faith, cuts not off from the Catholique Church, but a falſe opinion of God does.</hi>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:37695:68"/>
How then is that of <hi>S. Paul</hi> true, <hi>Heb. 11. 6. Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> Can a man violate Faith, though but in ſome one point, and yet be a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique? who ever thought ſo beſides your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf? by the ſame reaſon one and the ſame man may be at the ſame time both Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and Heretique. But to prove your new opinion, you produce an antient teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of S. <hi>Auguſtine, (de fid. &amp; Symb. c. 20.) Haereti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i de Deo falſa ſentiendo, ipſam fidem violant, quapropter non perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ad Eccleſiam Catholicam. Heretiques by having a falſe opinion of God, violate Faith it ſelf, wherefore they belong not to the Catholique Church. Anſw.</hi> Here is now a fine proof, if well examin'd. You muſt know Doctor, that the word [<hi>Quapropter] wherefore,</hi> refers to the words immediately going before; and then 'tis plain, that this teſtimony of the Father makes directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. For if men be therefore cut off from the Catholique Church, becauſe they have violated the Faith, then it neceſſarily follows, that every violation of Faith cuts a man off from the <hi>Catholique Church.</hi> But in favour to the Doctor, let us once grant againſt all reaſon, that the word [<hi>Quapropter</hi>] may refer to the former words, and that the Father ſpeaks as the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:37695:69"/>
Doctor would have him. What ſhall we diſcover then? even this conſequence, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques by having a falſe opinion of God are cut off from the Catholique Church; therefore every violation of Faith cuts not off from the Catholique Church.</hi> Moſt admirable! this is juſt like the reſt. If this be a good conſequence, there was never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bad or fallacious. Juſt ſo will I prove, that every damnable ſin excludes not a man from Gods favour. <hi>Murther and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery exclude a man from Gods favour; therefore not every damnable ſin excludes a man from Gods favour.</hi> You will ſay, this is no good conſequence; I ſay ſo too, but I am ſure it is as good as yours, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame with yours.</p>
            <p>70. Now we come to examine who are in <hi>Schiſm,</hi> the Church, or <hi>Luthers</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers; or indeed, rather whether there be any Schiſm or no, between the Church of Rome and the Proteſtants, which the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſeems to deny. The truth is, M. <hi>T. B.</hi> has ſo gravel'd the poor Doctor, that he is forc't to fly to moſt miſerable and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſhifts. M. <hi>T. B.</hi> very rationally and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly ſayes, by way of objection, that <hi>Chriſts myſtical Body is but one; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Body be made up of divers mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, yet all theſe members muſt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:37695:69"/>
one with another; for if a member be ſeparated but by Schiſm, it is like an arm cut off from the Body, or a branch from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine, which makes that arm or branch no part of the Body or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine.</hi> To this the Doctor anſwers thus, <hi>What though all this be granted, will this make one of the two no Church? I believe not. Reply.</hi> 'Tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry likely Doctor that you believe ſo, but what man of ſenſe or underſtanding can believe ſo? Can a particular church ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the whole Catholique Church, both in Doctrines of Faith and external communion, and yet not be Schiſmatical, but ſtill continue a Catholique Church? who ever before D. <hi>Boughen</hi> could ſay or think ſo? Well, but S. <hi>Pauls</hi> authority is alledged, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 25. where it is ſaid, that all the members of the body muſt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate one with another, in the ſame care one for another, in the ſame ſufferings and rejoycings one with another. What then? Is there no other communion neceſſary to avoid Schiſm? This is juſt like your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conſequences, <hi>The members muſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate one with another in the ſame ſufferings and rejoycings one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; therefore to avoid Schiſm, there is no other communion neceſſary.</hi> I am ſure, this is no neceſſary conſequence; but with
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:37695:70"/>
ſuch poor fallacies as theſe, Heretiques have always endeavour'd to deceive the world. Neither can that place of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage you at all; for he there only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares Chriſt's myſtical body, the Church, to the natural body; and ſayes, that as all the members of the natural body mutually aſſiſt each other, and without any Schiſm, that is, any diviſion, or diſcord, joyntly concur to preſerve the body; ſo alſo in the Church, which is Chriſts myſtical body, there are different orders, functions, and offices, all which ought mutually to aſſiſt each other for the preſervation of the whole church: this is al that S. <hi>Paul</hi> intends in that place, as by the context of the whole cha. wil evidently appear to any indifferent Reader.</p>
            <p>71. <hi>We are not bound</hi> (you ſay, Sect. 32.) <hi>to communicate with the Church of Rome in the ſame ceremonies, geſture, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, or error. Anſw.</hi> Firſt, I deny that the Roman Church is, or ever was, or can be guilty of ſuperſtition, or error in faith. Secondly, I grant that you are bound not to communicate with any Nation, or people in ſuperſtition, or error; As alſo, that you are not bound to uſe the ceremonies of other Catholique Churches. There be divers particular Churches that differ from each other in ſome ceremonies, and yet are
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:37695:70"/>
in perfect charity, and communicate with each other. As for example, The <hi>Weſterne Church</hi> conſecrates in unleavened bread, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of our B. Saviour, who firſt inſtituted the bleſſed Sacrament, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated in unleavened bread; but the <hi>Greeke Church</hi> has alwaies accuſtomed to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate in leavened bread: beſides, theſe two Churches differ in divers ceremonies of the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> though not in any ſubſtantiall or eſſentiall part thereof. And yet theſe two churches are in perfect charity and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with each other. (I ſpeak here of the true Catholique <hi>Greek Church,</hi> not of thoſe ſchiſmatiq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and Heretiques, who have cut themſelves off from the Catholique Church; whom notwithſtanding you are pleas'd to cal the <hi>Greeke Church.</hi>) Neither doe thoſe churches abhorre each others ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies as ſuperſtitious or unlawfull, but the particular members of each church are moſt ready to conforme to the ceremonies and diſcipline of each other, according as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſhall travell or paſſe from one church to the other. As when a biſhop or Prieſt of the Eaſterne church travells into any part of the Weſterne, he then makes me ſcruple to conſecrate in unleavened bread, as formerly in his own church he conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in leavened; but when any two churches
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:37695:71"/>
ſhall abhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and deteſt the Doctrine and ceremonies of each other, as hereticall, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious, idolatrous, and repugnant to plaine <hi>Scripture,</hi> there is then a perfect ſchiſme. And ſince theſe two abhorre each others communion, charging each other with ſacrilegious, idolatrous, and damnable errours, they cannot both meet in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church; and therefore one of them muſt neceſſarily be cut off from Chriſt's myſticall body, either by hereſie or ſchiſme, or both. Wherefore in granting that aſſertion of Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> you muſt alſo grant, that either the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Proteſtants, are guilty of hereſie, or ſchiſme, or both; and therefore no part of the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>72. It is then now time to ſhow who is the ſchiſmatique. And that you are ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall, I prove thus.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that have ſeperated themſelves from the communion of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, are ſchiſmaticall.</p>
            <p>But you have ſeparated your ſelves from the communion of the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo.</hi> You are Schiſmaticall.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is evident, and often granted by the Doctor; the <hi>minor</hi> is thus prov'd.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that have ſeparated themſelves
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:37695:71"/>
from the communion of the biſhop and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>But you have ſeperated your ſelves from the communion of the biſhop, and Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo.</hi> You have ſeparated your ſelves from the communion of the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>The <hi>minor</hi> is acknowledg'd by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, Sect. 19. of his firſt <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The <hi>major</hi> is ſufficiently proved, Sect, 25. and Sect. 58. wherefore I will here only add ſome few authentique teſtimonies more in proofe thereof. S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſayes, (<hi>li. 4. ep. 8. a d Corn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Pontif.) Placuit ut per Epiſcopos, reteni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> à nobis rei veritate ad comprobandam ordinationem tuam, &amp;c. ut te univerſi Collegae noſtri, &amp; commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicationem tuam, id eſt, Catholicae Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae unitatem pariter &amp; charitatem proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent firmiter &amp; tenerent. Wee thought fit, &amp;c. that all our fellow biſhops might ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly approve of and imbrace you, and your communion, that is, the Catholique Churches unity and charity.</hi> Is it not plaine by theſe words, that the unity of the Catholique Church conſiſts in the communion with the Biſhop of <hi>Rome?</hi> And if there be no Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique unity, but in communion with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:37695:72"/>
of <hi>Rome;</hi> it is apparently impoſſible, that any one can be united to the Catholique Church, that is not in communion with the Biſhop and the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Beſides, that the Church is built upon S. <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſors, I have already fully proved. Sect. 25. and Sect. 58. to which I will add one teſtimonie more out of S. <hi>Cyprian. (Epiſt. ad Quintinum.) Nam nec</hi> Petrus, <hi>quem primum elegit, &amp; ſuper quem ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dificavit Eccleſiam ſuam &amp;c. For neither Peter, whom our Lord choſe to be the firſt, and upon whom he built his Church.</hi> &amp;c. The like words he has (<hi>Ser. 3. de bon. pat.</hi>) whoſoever then forſakes the foundation, cannot be part of the houſe or building. The whole building reſts upon the foundation; wherfore he that is ſeparated from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, is ſeparated alſo from the building, which is the houſe, the Church of God. And you muſt remember, <hi>Doctor,</hi> that S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> liv'd in the yeare of Chriſt 250. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore long within the firſt 500. yeares, to which you have appeal'd, Sect. 27. ſo that you muſt either confeſſe the Proreſtants to be out of the communion of the Catholique Church, and conſequently ſchiſmaticall, at the leaſt; or elſe you muſt revoke and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce your appeale.</p>
            <p>If you will ſay, that the ſenſe of the whole
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:37695:72"/>
Church appeares not fully in the writings of particular Fathers; you ſhall heare the confeſſion and acknowledgment of 520. Fathers aſſembled in the fourth Generall Councell at <hi>Calcedon,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt 451. who all unanimouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Pope <hi>Leo</hi> their head. Their words are; <hi>Quibus tu quidem ſicut membris caput praeras, Over whom</hi> (that is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers aſſembled in the Councell) <hi>thou wert as the Head over the members.</hi> And it is to be obſerv'd, that this Councell was held in the Eaſterne Church, and conſiſted for the moſt part of the Fathers of that Church; wherein notwithſtanding Pope <hi>Leo's</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates ſate in the uppermoſt Seat, and took place of the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtant inople</hi> himſelf, even in his own Patriarchate; which would never have been permited, had not the Pope's Juriſdiction extended to the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern, as wel as the Weſtern Churches. About 50. yeares after the Councell, did not the Eaſtern biſhops acknowledge that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for all Chriſtians to communicate with the biſhop and Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> you have heard, Sect. 58. that <hi>Iohn</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of Conſtantinople excluded al from the communion of the Catholique Church, that were divided from the <hi>Apoſtolique ſea</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> which, doubtleſſe, the great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:37695:73"/>
of the <hi>Eaſt</hi> would never have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, had it not deſcended by univerſall Tradition, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt to be the ſupreme Paſtor and Governour of the whole Church. Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all this Patriarch's letters written to Pope <hi>Hormiſda,</hi> and you ſhall find them all directed to the Pope, after this manner. <hi>Domino m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o per omnia ſanctiſſimo.</hi> And can any reaſonable man imagine, that ſo great a Patriarch would have ſtiled the Pope, <hi>his Lord,</hi> if his power in the Eaſterne Church had been abſolute, and independent on the ſea of <hi>Rome?</hi> In like manner <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> in the Eaſtern Church, in his Epiſtle to the ſame Pope has theſe words. <hi>Iſta nunc ſcripſi Beato Capiti noſtro per Patricium. &amp;c.</hi> Theſe things have I now written by <hi>Patricius</hi> to our <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this it plainly appeares, that in thoſe dayes, within the firſt 600. yeares of <hi>Christ,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was acknowledg'd the <hi>Head</hi> of the Eaſtern Churches, as well as of the Weſtern; and that by the Eaſtern Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops themſelves, even by their cheife, and Head-Biſhop, the Patriarch of the Eaſt; who likewiſe (as you have already heard) confeſt, that all Catholique Communion flowes from the Apoſtolique ſea of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:37695:73"/>
as the Head and Fountain thereof. And what better interpreter of Scripture, or more faithful preſerver of Apoſtolique Traditions can therebe, then the antient and univerſal practiſe of the Church?</p>
            <p>To the practiſe of former Ages, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations of antient Councels, let us joyn the defini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions of later times, viz. of the Councel of <hi>Florence,</hi> in the year 1439. where the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was preſent in perſon, and all the other Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, either perſonally, or by their Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates. Let us then hear the whole Church ſpeaking in that Councel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item definimus Sanctam Apoſtolicam ſedem, &amp; Romanum Pontificem in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſum Orbem tenere primatum, &amp;c.</hi> (Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Florent. Act. ult.) <hi>Alſo we declare, that the holy Apoſtolique Sea and Biſhop of Rome hath the primacy over the whole world, and that the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>is S.</hi> Peters <hi>Succeſſor, who was chief of the Apoſtles, and that he is Chriſt's true Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car, and Head of the whole Church, the Father and Doctor of all Chriſtians; and that in</hi> S. Peter <hi>full power was given to him (the Biſhop of Rome) by our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ, to feed, rule, and govern the whole Church.</hi> To this definition ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed all the Patriarchs of the Church, and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:37695:74"/>
amongſt the reſt the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> himſelf. You ſhall have his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, as it is ſet down in the Acts of the Councel. <hi>Joſeph miſerations divinâ Conſtantinopolis, &amp;c.</hi> Florent. An. 1439. <hi>I</hi> Joſeph, <hi>by the mercy of God, Arch-biſhop of Conſtantinople, and new Rome, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Patriarch, becauſe my life is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt at an end, do therefore by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, according to my duty, publiſh this my opinion to my beloved ſons in this writing. For all thoſe things which our Lord Jeſus Chriſts Catholique and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique Church of Old Rome believes and imbraces, I profeſs that I alſo do hold and believe, and fully conſent unto them. And I grant, that the bleſſed Father of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and chief Prieſt, the Pope of Old Rome, is our Lord Ieſus Chriſts <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>car, and I deny not that there is a Purgatory for ſouls.</hi> And note, that this is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of a dying man paſt hope of life. Here you ſee a concurrence of the later a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with the former. Here you ſee all the churches of the world conſenting to the Primacy and Juriſdiction of the Church of Rome. Here you have ſeen the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the antient church, the Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of former Councels, and the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of later; then which nothing can
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:37695:74"/>
better interpret Scripture, or more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerve divine truths and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Doctrines to poſterity.</p>
            <p>Since then the Church of Rome is the <hi>Head</hi> and Mother-church of the world, and conſequently the Fountain of Unity, whoſoever ſhall ſeparate himſelf from her communion, cannot poſſibly be a member of the Catholique Church: And ſince the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by her power and Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction diffuſes her ſelf over all the parts of the Chriſtian world, and as being the great Metropolitan of the world, infuſes unity into all particular Churches and Chriſtians, She is in this her largeſt ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude properly and truly call'd the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church.</hi> And becauſe the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church cannot fall into any error in faith, or any other damnable error whatſoever, nor teach Doctrines ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, ſacrilegious, or repugnant to plain words of Scripture, becauſe ſhe is, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be guided by Gods Holy Spirit, which hitherto has, and ever ſhall lead her into all truth, therefore it cannot be truly ſaid, that the Roman Church being this Catholique Church, ever was, or can be guilty of errors in faith, or of ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſacrilegious, or any damnable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:37695:75"/>73. Beſides, when <hi>Luther</hi> firſt for ſook the communion of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> did he not ſtand alone? was he not divided from the world, even from thoſe that were not in communion with the Church of Rome, as well as from thoſe that were? did he communicate in the Sacraments, or external worſhip with any particular Church, Congregation, People, Nation, or Sect profeſſing the name of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> can any man ſeparate himſelf from that church, in whoſe communion he once liv'd, whoſe Faith and Doctrine he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac't, and joyn himſelf to no other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in the whole world, profeſſing the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> either in doctrine or external communion, and yet be no Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matique? If ſo, then there never was, or can be any Schiſm. If then <hi>Luther</hi> was Schiſmatical in being divided from the Whole Chriſtian world in Faith and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, it neceſſarily follows, that all thoſe who firſt adhered to him, forſaking the communion of that church, whereof they had formerly been members, and all thoſe who have ſince followed <hi>Luther,</hi> and have not joyn'd themſelves to any church or <hi>Chriſtian Congregation</hi> whatſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides themſelves, muſt be guilty of the ſame Schiſm. How then is it poſſible for you to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:37695:75"/>
avoid the guilt of Schiſm, ſince you have forſaken the communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with whom you once communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as you confeſs, Sect. 19. and have not joyn'd your ſelves to any other <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Congregation</hi> whatſoever? You ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the communion of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and that which you call the <hi>Greek Church</hi> abhors you. Will you ſay, that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants are the whole Catholique Church? then you contradict your ſelf, who grant Sect. 12. that <hi>Rome her ſelf is a Church, a member of the one Catholique.</hi> You muſt alſo then confeſs, that the Greek Church (as you call it) is no part of the Catholique Church, and the truth is, you have good reaſon ſo to do, ſince ſhe refuſed to receive you into her communio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, abhorring and deteſting your new Doctrines, as heretical: If then all thoſe of the Proteſtant Sect be Schiſmatical (as it moſt plainly appears they are) certainly the Proteſtants of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> muſt neceſſarily be involv'd in the ſame Schiſm.</p>
            <p>74. Let us now ſee how you can vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate your ſelves from hereſie. I will not look beyond thoſe four Doctrines where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have charg'd the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as being fond, ſacrilegious, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to plain words of Scripture,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:37695:76"/>
viz. <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Adminiſtration of the B. Sacrament to the Laity in one kind; Invocation of Saints; Adoration of Images.</hi> And by your oppoſing theſe doctrines as they are held and taught by the Roman Church, I ſhall endeavour to make it appear to the world, that you cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the juſt imputation of Hereſie.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I demand, whether the Fathers aſſembled in the four firſt General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels were not competent and lawful Judges of the hereſies of thoſe times; as the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, Macedonian, Neſtorian, Eutychian, &amp;c.</hi> and whether they had not power to condemn thoſe hereſies, and to anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize thoſe that held and taught them as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques. If they had no ſuch power, then did they moſt injuriouſly and tyrannically uſurp a power and Juriſdiction, which of right belonged not unto them. But this cannot be prudently ſuppos'd, that ſo many holy, reverend, and learned Fathers ſhould uſurp an authority, or arrogate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that power, which was not lawfully deriv'd upon them by Chriſt and his holy church: They were the ſelected Paſtors of the whole church, men renowned for their piety and learning, and could not therefore be ignorant how far the Juriſdiction and authority of a lawful Councel might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend;
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:37695:76"/>
neither would their piety ſuffer them to tranſgreſs the limits of that authority. If then thoſe four firſt Councels had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to judg of, and to decla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and define doctrines of faith, and to anathematize all thoſe that ſhould oppoſe them; how came the Councels in ſucceeeding ages to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of this power? How came the church to loſe that authority wherewith ſhe was once inveſted? was her power but tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, and after ſome few ages to expire? or did Chriſt foreſee, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after ſome few ages his church would be no more infeſted with Schiſmatiques, or heretiques? but we plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find, that ſuch have moleſted the church in all ages, and therefore doubtleſs in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges has this power continued in the church; and if ſo, why was it not as lawful for the ſecond Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> (which was held above 800. years ſince) to judg and define what reverence and honor is due to holy I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; and to condemn the <hi>Iconoclaſts</hi> or Image-breakers, as it was for the former Councels to condemn the <hi>Arrians, Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, &amp;c?</hi> And why was it not as lawful for that great and glorious Councel of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> wherein were preſent both the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> to judg of, and declare the true, real, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial converſion of the creatures of bread
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:37695:77"/>
and wine after conſecration, into the true and real body and bloud of Chriſt; and to declare the manner of that converſion, as alſo to expreſs the antient doctrine of the church by the proper ſignification of a new word [<hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi>] as it was for the firſt General Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> to judg of, and declare <hi>Chriſts conſubstantiality</hi> with the Father, and to invent that new word to expreſs the antient doctrine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending unto them by univerſal and in fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Tradition of Chriſts co-eternal and co-equal <hi>Divinity</hi> with the Father? You wil find in <hi>Vincentius Lyrineſis. c.</hi> 32. that it was no new thing in his time for the church to invent new words to expreſs old doctrines.</p>
            <p>Why was it not lawful for the Councel of <hi>Conſtance (Seſſ.</hi> 13.) to define and declare the indifferency and ſufficiency of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating the Laity under one kind only, and to anathematize thoſe that ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinatiouſly oppoſe that doctrine?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, why was it not lawful for the Councel of <hi>Trent (Seſſ.</hi> 25.) to declare the lawfulneſs of invocating the bleſſed Saints, and to denounce a curſe againſt all obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate oppoſers thereof?</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee thoſe four fond and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious doctrines, and ſuch as you ſay are repugnant to plain words of <hi>Scripture,</hi>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:37695:77"/>
confirm'd, declar'd, and defin'd to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred truths, and Apoſtolical Traditions by four General Councels. You have alſo ſeen them held and practis'd by the antient Fathers, that liv'd within the firſt 500. years of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> Sect. 35. 36. 37. 38. &amp;c. what can you ſay for your ſelves? what can you plead for your ſelves, that you, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Doctrines of the church, ſhould not incur the penalty of the curſe?</p>
            <p>75. You will ſay, perchance, that theſe are not Doctrines and Declarations of the whole Church Catholique, but of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> only, and thoſe in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with her, which you ſay is but part of the <hi>Catholike Church.</hi> But this wil not now ſerve your turn: whether the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and thoſe in communion with her, be a part only of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> or the whole <hi>Catholike Church</hi> it ſelf, (as I have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prov'd it is) it matters not, you cannot be excus'd from hereſie. For when <hi>Luther</hi> was a Fryer, before he ſet himſelf againſt the church, what church? what congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> what Nation? what peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? nay, what man was there in the whole world, profeſſing the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that denied or oppoſed thoſe, or any one of thoſe forementioned Doctrines? Theſe were doctrines receiv'd, imbrac't, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely profeſt by the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world.
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:37695:78"/>
Not the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> and thoſe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with her only, but thoſe alſo that were out of her communion (as the whole pretended <hi>Greek Church</hi>) receiv'd and profeſt theſe doctrines in their univerſal, publike and daily practiſe; as appears by <hi>Jeremias Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in his <hi>ſententia deſinitiva de doctrina &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione Wittenberg en ſium Proteſtanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m:</hi> as alſo in his <hi>Cenſura Orientalis Eccleſiae;</hi> where you ſhall find a deteſtation of your oppoſite doctrines.</p>
            <p>76. But if thoſe doctrine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be fond, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious, and repugnant to plain words of Scripture, where was the church, that pillar and ground of truth, when the whole Chriſtian world, before <hi>Luthers</hi> apoſtaſie, receiv'd, held, and maintain'd them? and if thoſe that ſhall thus ſeparate themſelves from, and oppoſe the whole church in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of faith, receiv'd by the whole church as ſuch, and acknowledg'd by her to be of univerſal and Apoſtolical tradition, be not heretiques, there never was, neither is it poſſible that there ever ſhould be any heretique in the world. And yet yours was no ſeparation, but a reformatſon. But what can be invented more abſurd or ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, then that one ſingle apoſtate in <hi>Germany,</hi> or a few <hi>avaricious</hi> and flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Courtiers</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> ſhould firſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:37695:78"/>
the communion of that church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they had liv'd from their <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and wherein all their forefathers for almoſt 1000. years liv'd and died, and afterwards renounce doctrines of Faith univerſally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by the church, and then take upon them to be Judges of the whole church, which Chriſt has made the Supreme Judg of all controverſies, and to reform the whole church, and that in matters of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? but you muſt know Doctor, that the <hi>Catholique Church</hi> cannot teach, or maintain ſacrilegious doctrines, or ſuch as are repugnaut to plain words of <hi>Scripture:</hi> For then ſhe would ceaſe to be <hi>holy,</hi> and conſequently to be a church, <hi>holineſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſſential to Gods church; as appeares both by the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles Creed:</hi> If then the church ſhould obtrude upon the world ſacrilegious and idolatrous doctrines, and ſuch as are repugnant to plain words of <hi>Scripture,</hi> inſtead of ſacred and divine truths, ſhe could not poſſibly be holy. Since then the whole Chriſtian world, when <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> was a <hi>Fryer,</hi> taught and maintain'd thoſe four foremention'd Doctrines, which you are pleas'd to ſtile, <hi>ſacrilegious, and repugnans to plain words of Scripture,</hi> it muſt neceſſarily follow, that either at that time God had no church at all (which
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:37695:79"/>
your ſelf confeſs to be impoſſible, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls that thoſe doctrines are not ſacrilegious, or repugnant to plain words of <hi>Scripture,</hi> but ſacred and Apoſtolical truths; and if ſo, what are thoſe that oppoſe and contradiet them?</p>
            <p>77. Hence it appears, how falſe that is which you ſay, <hi>Sect. 32. That you commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with the Church of Rome in neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in Faith, Hope and Charity,</hi> &amp;c. ſince you oppoſe her in doctrines of <hi>Faith;</hi> and by your ſchiſme (a ſin directly againſt <hi>Charity</hi>) have cut your ſelves off from her communion. With what face then can you ſay, <hi>Sect. 34. That you abhor not mutual communion with her in divine worſhip.</hi> Do you not abhor to communicate with her in the Sacraments? Do you not call her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of Chriſt in the B. Sacrament <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry?</hi> And whereas you ſay there, <hi>that you cannot endure that divine worſhip be given to any other then to the B. Trinity;</hi> I would have you know, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> gives not divive worſhip to any thing but God; and if you will ſay that ſhe does, you will but proove your ſelf very malicious or very ignorant.</p>
            <p>78. In your 35 <hi>Sect.</hi> I find nothing, but what is either impertinent, or already an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:37695:79"/>79. In the next <hi>Sect.</hi> I meet with a bold challenge. <hi>I challenge</hi> (ſaies the Doctor) <hi>the moſt able of your faction to ſhew me any one paſſage in our Common-Prayer Book, that is not Catholique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If your Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> be Catholique, yet you have no great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to boaſt of it; you may thank the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for it, from whom you borrowed it: which you know <hi>Doctor,</hi> was the principal reaſon, why thoſe of the <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> faction refuſ'd and abhor'd your Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> as being <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>ſuper ſtitious.</hi> But if all in that Book be Catholique, it is rather an argument, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is Catholique, from whence you took it, then that you are ſo. For all in that Book may be Catholique, yet you may be Heretical. You may oppoſe, as you do, other doctrines of Faith, that are not contained in, nor deducible from your Book of <hi>Common Prayer.</hi> And if about the beginning of your defection ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques frequented your Service; it was becauſe they eſteemed it devout and pious, as being all taken out of the <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> They had not fully conſidered, nor yet cleerly apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the unlawfulneſs thereof. Wherefore it behoved the common Paſtor of Gods
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:37695:80"/>
Church to put them in mind, how impious and ſacrilegious it was for Catholiques to communicate with thoſe, who were guilty both of Schiſm and Hereſie, in divine Service.</p>
            <p>80. And whereas you alledg S. <hi>Paul</hi> to prove that in meats and matters of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency, we are not to judge one another; you muſt know, Doctor, that Doctrines of faith, (ſuch as are Declarations, and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of Generall Councells) the lawes and Canons of the Vniverſall Church, made, and generally receiv'd by the Church, as the ancient Canons concerning Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valls, and Faſts, are not matters of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency; and cannot be violated without ſchiſm or Hereſie.</p>
            <p>81. But I wonder with what face you can call your Congregation the Mother-Church of Catholiques, Sect. 39. 'Tis you that have forſaken your Mother-Church, that Church wherein all your fore-fathers liv'd and died, for about. 1000. yeares together. you confeſſe that once you communicated with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that ſince you have forſaken her communion. Is it fit that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whom you have forſaken, ſhould ſtoop to you? Is ſhe bound to follow you that have forſaken her? who made you Judges of Gods Church, that you
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:37695:80"/>
ſhould take upon you to charge the whole Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with errours, both in faith and manners? by what rule have you done this? you pretend Sect. 37. to walke by a ſure rule; but I am ſure you walke not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of Chriſt's Catholique Church. For ſhe walks according to the rule of Gods Word, interpreted by univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall and Apoſtolicall tradition, which you contemne and laugh at: but you, by the rule of Scripture interpreted by your own private fancies, and deceiptfull imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>82. Now the Doctor begins to quarrel with the Language of the Church of <hi>Rome How do they</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>pray with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who pray in a tongue, the people under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not? Anſw.</hi> And why may not Preiſt and people joyne in heart to God in prayer, though the language of the Churches prayers be not underſtood by all preſent? S. <hi>Paul</hi> confeſſes, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 14. that a man may pray in ſpirit, in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne tongue, though not with his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. The Prieſt and people of the Jewes could joyne together in prayer, and prayers to God, before Chriſt; though their Service were perform'd in the Hebrew Tongue, a language no more then under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the vulgar Jewes, then the <hi>Latin</hi>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:37695:81"/>
is now by the vulgar Chriſtians, why then may not the Chriſtian Preiſt and people joyne together in prayer, though the church Service be perform'd in a language, which ſome of the vulgar Chriſtians, that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, underſtand not? The <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Tongues, wherein only the church Service has been perform'd through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Chriſtian world ever ſince the time of the Apoſtles, are languages well knowne to the world: all men may learne them. They are not ſuch unknowne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages as thoſe were, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. which were miraculouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd into many of the Primitive Chriſtians, the end whereof was the edification of the church, and the converſion of Infidells. Now thoſe tongues were neither underſtood by the people, nor alwaies by thoſe that ſpake them, as appeares, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 13. Theſe languages miraculouſly infus'd by God, the Primitive Chriſtians uſed in their publique meetings; firſt to inſtruct the ignorant; ſecondly to convert Infidells; where their inſtructions and prayers were alwayes extemporary, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they were immediately aſſiſted by Gods holy Spirit. But the publique prayers of the church are not in ſuch unknowne languages. Secondly, they are ſaid in the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:37695:81"/>
ſame languages, wherein the publique Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the church was ever performed in all ages ſince the Apoſtles, as appeares by the antient <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin Miſſales;</hi> which is an argument unanſwerable, that ſuch languages are not againſt S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. nor any other place of Gods Word. Thirdly; the end of our preſent publique meetings in the church, is not to inſtruct, edifie, or convert, as thoſe meetings were, whereof S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes in that chapter; but to offer up to God the tribute of prayer and praiſes that is due unto him; as alſo to draw downe Gods bleſſings, both ſpirituall and temporall upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And to this end the people joyne with the Prieſt in their exteriour acts of devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Religion, thereby profeſſing their aſſent to the publique prayers, and praiſes of the Church. And can it be thought neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for thoſe ends, that all the people pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſhould expreſly underſtand every word of the Churches Service, which though it were in the vulgar language of every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, would notwithſtanding be impoſſible?</p>
            <p>83. <hi>Between the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches,</hi> you ſay, Sect. 40. <hi>there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny differences &amp;c. and yet for all theſe they grew up together comfortably, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſame body. Anſw.</hi> When the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:37695:82"/>
differences between the Eaſtern and We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Churches were concerning ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as were not declar'd in any Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell, nor could appeare by the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall tradition or practiſe of the Church, they were then only errours, not hereſies: but when any of the Eaſterne Churches op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Weſtern in ſuch Doctrines as appear'd either in the practiſe of the Church, or by univerſall tradition, and conſent of Nations, or were declar'd and defin'd in a Generall Councell, they then fell from errour into hereſie; and were thereby cut off from the Catholique Church.</p>
            <p>Your 41. Sect. is anſwer'd, Sect. 29. and Sect. 65. and Sect. 30. 84. In your 42. Sect. you ſay, <hi>That the keyes were given to all the Apoſtles alike. Anſw.</hi> This I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe in ſome ſenſe may be true, but makes nothing for you. That all the Apoſtles had the keyes of remitting and retaining ſins, is true. I can grant alſo, that they were all univerſall Biſhops, yet they had not all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually the keyes of externall government and Juriſdiction. S. <hi>Iohn</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi> had not that power, which S. <hi>Peter</hi> had at <hi>Antioch,</hi> or afterwards at <hi>Rome.</hi> For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever S. <hi>Peter</hi> was, he had a Juriſdiction over the reſt of the Apoſtles, as well as the whole Church beſides, which S. <hi>John</hi> never had.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:37695:82"/>Your, 43. Sect. has been already fully anſwer'd.</p>
            <p>Sect. 58. In your, 44. Sect. you ſay, out of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy. 2. Timoth. 3, 15. That the Scripture is able to make us wiſe unto ſalvation; and that you are reſolved by Gods grace to accept of nothing, but what is deduced from thence, or proved thereby, according to the interpretation of the ancient Fathers and Councells.</hi> That of S. <hi>Paul</hi> I confeſſe; and withall very glad that you have made ſo good a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. If you ſhall conſtantly perſiſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſhall receive no interpretation of <hi>Scripture</hi> but from the ancient Fathers, Councells, and the tradition of the Church (as <hi>Vincentius Lyrinenſis</hi> adviſes you, <hi>ch.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) you will ſoone become <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your 45. and laſt Sect. containes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what has been by you ſaid before, and by me ſufficiently anſwer'd, Sect. 18. and. Sect. 21. 29. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I have done with your <hi>Anſwer,</hi> and now crave leave to ſpeake ſomewhat to you by way of exhortation in the Spirit of meekneſſe.</p>
            <p>You have hitherto been a guide to others; let not a vaine feare, or apprehenſion of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſhonour that may eclipſe your former
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:37695:83"/>
reputation, by confeſſing your errours, and that you have been a blind leader of the blind, come between you and your eternall Salvation. Let not the deceitfull luſtre of vaine glory tempt you to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſerve your cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the world, with the loſſe of Heaven. You owe God your reputation as well as your life, or whatſoever elſe is moſt deare unto you: conſider at how deare a rate <hi>Christ</hi> purchas'd the Redemption of your Soul: deſtroy not then that ſoul for which <hi>Chrict</hi> died. Let not pride, prejudice, or or malice caſt a miſt before the eyes of your underſtanding; and you ſhall ſoone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that light, which will infallibly guide you to your laſt end, <hi>God;</hi> and the eternall friution of the <hi>Beatificall Viſion.</hi> Gods can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, ſince it was firſt lighted by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> was never put under a buſhell; but from the candleſtick wherein it was firſt ſet, has given light to the world; and all eyes, that are not blinded with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or intereſt, muſt behold it. You ſeeme to approve the Principles of <hi>Vinceutius Lyrinenſis;</hi> follow them, and you are ſafe. Let <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality</hi> be your guide, and you cannot erre. Let not ſome few ſcatter'd, obſcure, and miſ-underſtood places of ſome Fathers prevaile more with you, then a thouſand plaine places, whole
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:37695:83"/>
treatiſes and volumnes purpoſely pen'd in defence of Catholique truth. Diveſt your ſoul of pride, malice, and intereſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof let humility and impartiality take place, and then Gods grace will ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly invite you to a ſincere and humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of your errors, and you will with exceſſive joy and thankfulneſs of heart praiſe <hi>God</hi> for your deliverance from the bonds of darkneſs, and the jawes of death. Remember that the antient Fathers and Doctors of the church have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd you, the Councels both Oecume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical and Provincial have declar'd againſt you; the univerſal doctrine and practiſe of the church, both before and after <hi>Luthers</hi> Apoſtaſie, have given ſentence againſt you. And as for thoſe <hi>Canons,</hi> which you have alledged in your book, you muſt needs know your ſelf, that ſome of them make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, others are impertinent, but none of them impugne the power and authority of <hi>Chriſts Vicar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> (the Biſhop of Rome) over the whole <hi>Catholique Church.</hi> Weigh all the Authorities of holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> and <hi>antiquity</hi> for both ſides; and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be not a thouſand plain places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, for one obſcure (for plain you have none) for you, Your eternal ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lyes at ſtake, rely not then on other
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:37695:84"/>
mens, nor your own fallacious judgment, or fancy, in thoſe things that concern your ſalvation. Let Gods holy church be your guide and interpreter of <hi>Scripture,</hi> leſt you wreſt it (as ſome did of whom S. <hi>Peter</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 16.) to your own damnation: conſider that the beſt way to appeaſe Gods wrath againſt you for your former miſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and ſeducing poor ignorant ſouls to their eternal perdition, is now by your good example, in returning to your holy Mother the <hi>Roman Catholique Church,</hi> to draw o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers after you into the houſe of God, his <hi>Church Militant;</hi> that ſo hereafter ye may meet in his <hi>Church Triumphant.</hi> Let not thoſe trifles of popular applauſe, or world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reputation flatter you to hell, nor fear of the worlds cenſure fright you from heaven; be but humble and impartial, and it is as impoſſible for you not to be a <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique</hi> (at leaſt in judgment and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) as it is for a man, that has the benefit of ſight to open his eys, and not to ſee light at noon day,</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Doctor,</hi> If you have met with any tart language in this my anſwer, you cannot juſtly be offended with me. It pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not from any malice that I can bear your perſon. For I profeſs upon the word of a Chriſtian, I never heard of your name
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:37695:84"/>
(to my remembrance) before I ſaw this your book; and I am ſtill ſo much a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to you, that I know neither the place of your abode, nor the preſent condition of your life. But I was ſomewhat provok't by your bleſphemous ſpeeches againſt Gods holy church by your unneceſſary taunts, and cauſleſs jeering of Mr. <hi>T. B.</hi> whoſe modeſty in his letters to you was ſuch, that I am ſure he gave you no juſt cauſe to break out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch ſcurrilous and unſeemly ſpeeches againſt him.</p>
            <p>I ſhall heartily pray, that inſtead of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to this anſwer, you may be reconcil'd to Gods holy <hi>Catholique Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:37695:85"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IF the</hi> Doctor or <hi>or any of his Party, be yet unſatisfied in this Controverſie, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that, rather then beſtow a Reply to theſe curſory Papers of mine, the moſt Learned of them would conſiderately exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> Mr. Creſſy's Exomologeſis, <hi>or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of his converſion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> Ruſhworths Dialogues, <hi>in the laſt Edition, as it is corrected and enlarged by</hi> Mr. Thomas White, <hi>in a 80, of the</hi> Long-Primer <hi>letter; both which they muſt acknowledge to be as much unanſwerable, as theſe light papers of</hi> Dr. Boughons <hi>are fully anſwered.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 17. line 23. read, <hi>at</hi> Rome. p. 36. l. 18. r. <hi>were</hi> a great. p. 59. l. 18. r. <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tanean.</hi> p. 63. l. 21. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 65. l. 23. r. but <hi>a.</hi> p. 67. l. 24. r. verùm <hi>&amp;,</hi> and l. 25. <hi>non</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide. p. 78. l. 7. r. as <hi>well as.</hi> p. 79 l. 27. r. <hi>offerun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 82. l. 8. r. prayers <hi>made</hi> at. p. 86. l. 10. r. <hi>is it.</hi> p. 114. l. 7. r. <hi>ſixth</hi> Century. p. 115. l. 13. r. <hi>nor</hi> Apoſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 118. l. 11. r. <hi>odious.</hi> and l. laſt. r. your <hi>taxing.</hi> p. 119. l. 17. r. <hi>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fia.</hi> p. 126. l. 13. dele <hi>of.</hi> p. 127. l. 28. r. <hi>ad.</hi> p. 137. l. 27. r. makes <hi>no.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37695:85"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
